<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Wonderfull prophecies from the beginning of the monarchy of this land hidden vnder the parables of: Three young noble-men in a fiary fornace. A chast wife, and two old fornicators. The idol Belus and his dragon. Daniel in a den amid lyons. Their agreement with canonical prophecies: also in temperate defence of the apocryphals annexed to the canon of the Scriptures. Together with an essay touching the late prodigious comete; how farre forth the præsages thereof doe accord with such prophecies, as are found to pertaine to these our times. By all which, the discrete and wise in heart may gather touching things to come, what is forewarned vnto men; as for the general and publique, so also for their priuate and particular. By Robert Salter.</title>
            <author>Salter, Robert, fl. 1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 129 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11372</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21630</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112138</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847396</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847396</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12429</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11372)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12429)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1583:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Wonderfull prophecies from the beginning of the monarchy of this land hidden vnder the parables of: Three young noble-men in a fiary fornace. A chast wife, and two old fornicators. The idol Belus and his dragon. Daniel in a den amid lyons. Their agreement with canonical prophecies: also in temperate defence of the apocryphals annexed to the canon of the Scriptures. Together with an essay touching the late prodigious comete; how farre forth the præsages thereof doe accord with such prophecies, as are found to pertaine to these our times. By all which, the discrete and wise in heart may gather touching things to come, what is forewarned vnto men; as for the general and publique, so also for their priuate and particular. By Robert Salter.</title>
                  <author>Salter, Robert, fl. 1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iones dwelling in Red-crosse street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On the Book of Daniel.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Daniel --  Criticism, interpretation, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Comets --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12429:1"/>
            <p>WONDERFVLL PROPHECIES FROM THE BEGINNING of the Monarchy of this Land, hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vnder the PARABLES of:
<list>
                  <item>Three young Noble-men in a fiary Fornace.</item>
                  <item>A chaſt wife, and two old Fornicators.</item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> BELVS and his Dragon.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>DANIEL</hi> in a Den amid Lyons.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> agreement with <hi>Canonical</hi> Prophecies: Alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Temperate <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Apocryphals</hi> annexed to the Canon of the Scriptures. Together with an Eſſay touching the late Prodigious <hi>COMETE;</hi> how farre forth the Praeſages thereof doe accord with ſuch Prophecies, as are found to pertaine to theſe our times. By all which, the diſcrete and wiſe in heart may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther touching things to come, what is forewarned vnto Men; as for the <hi>General</hi> and Publique, ſo alſo for their <hi>Priuate</hi> and Particular.</p>
            <p>By ROBERT SALTER.</p>
            <q>
               <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hath foreſeene the euil and hideth himſelfe: but the raſh haue paſſed on and ſhall bee plagued.</p> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pro. 22.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by WILLIAM IONES dwelling in <hi>Red-croſſe ſtreete.</hi> 1626.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12429:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12429:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE EDMOND Lord SHEFFIELD, Baron of <hi>Butterwyke,</hi> Earle of <hi>Mulgraue,</hi> Knight of the moſt Noble Order of the <hi>Garter,</hi> and my ſingular good Lord, <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Light</hi> from God in the <hi>Loue</hi> of Chriſt,</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nthrifty</hi> kinde of Spirit is it, that the minde of <hi>the Man</hi> is now ſo obeſſed with! For what <hi>notion</hi> ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhall bee offered vnto it, differing but the leaſt point from the <hi>vulgar ayres</hi> which <hi>Praeiudice</hi> hath formerly taken hold off: howbeit there appeare, whether manifeſt <hi>Argument</hi> of <hi>Neceſsity,</hi> or ſtrong <hi>Inducement</hi> of <hi>Benefite;</hi> yet it is reproued and rejected onely for this; Becauſe it is <hi>NEW.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb facs="tcp:12429:3"/>
on the <hi>Contrary,</hi> let it preſent vs with <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> of <hi>delight,</hi> or <hi>choiſe</hi> of <hi>idleneſſe,</hi> though to the ineuitable <hi>deſtruction</hi> of <hi>one</hi> and <hi>all</hi> of vs, yet by how much the <hi>Newer</hi> it is, by ſo much the more is it honoured, rewarded, and <hi>greedily imbraced.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An <hi>Inſtance</hi> hereof, may bee the <hi>preſent</hi> ſtate of this our <hi>Chriſtian world,</hi> in whoſe greateſt part, this is found to be trew, that albeit there be tendered vnto vs, <hi>Stability</hi> of <hi>Eſtate, Treuth</hi> of <hi>Society, Peace</hi> and <hi>Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> on earth, and <hi>fauor</hi> with God and Man, ſuch, as <hi>greater</hi> the world neuer before en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed: yet is there no place of <hi>audience</hi> to be gotten, euen for none other reaſon but this. That the path is <hi>New</hi> and vntroden; And wee muſt not bee weained from walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on ſtill in the <hi>ſpiritual blindneſſes,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with wee haue hitherto like Mould-warpes beene holden and delighted, as if it were writen in <hi>Capital</hi> letters for a <hi>Frontiſpice,</hi> on the Gate of our <hi>common ſenſe [Non intret fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi.]</hi> Let not a good <hi>Obiect</hi> be admitted, nor a <hi>thought</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> be <hi>conceiued</hi> amongſt vs.</p>
            <p>Such lot hath this man of God, the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of theſe Parables, bin forced to paſſe
<pb facs="tcp:12429:3"/>
vnder. Concerning whom, becauſe in men of <hi>former</hi> times, there was onely a <hi>doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe,</hi> for they were vnto them <hi>(perhaps through their owne negligence)</hi> not yet vnſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; Therefore the men of our daies will out of a <hi>Preiudicate wilfulneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 9.</note> vtterly <hi>abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> them, and (as the <hi>Iewes</hi> did concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt) <hi>excommunicate</hi> as many as beare witneſſe to any of them, how well ſo euer they ſhall be by the <hi>Spirt of God</hi> opened, and how <hi>comfortable</hi> ſo euer the things contained in them bee found vnto vs. <hi>[Thus doe men loue darkeneſſe rather then light,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 3.</note> 
               <hi>leaſt their deedes ſhould be reproued.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the middeſt of ſo <hi>deſolate</hi> a wilderneſſe more diſordered then the brute ſea (for the Ocean hath <hi>kindly returnes</hi> of ebbes and flowes, and his <hi>Decumanos fluctus,</hi> I was by a <hi>Mighty</hi> hand guided, to the taking vp of this our <hi>Prophet,</hi> caſt out as condemned to perpetuall exyle, and not worthy the <hi>light of the Sun of Righteouſneſse in his Church,</hi> when viewing well, I could diſcerne in him the life of <hi>Diuine ſeede;</hi> which I acknowleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my ſelfe bound by the lawes of <hi>Nature, common to vs both,</hi> to foſter and cheriſh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:12429:4"/>
full growth, according to the beſt skill of my <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> and <hi>light</hi> in heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Myſteries.</hi> Wherefore I profered him my ſeruice and helpe, which euen at the very firſt was ſo chearefully accepted of him, that he immediately directed me to preſent him to you my excellent good Lord, with aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of good ſpeed therby<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherfore with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay I haſted to accompliſh this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, neither hath my expectation erred for the <hi>Gratious</hi> enterteynment hee found at his firſt acceſſe to your Preſence: ſimply clad (as he was) in <hi>Pilgrims</hi> Habit: No more then was ſufficient to auow him one of <hi>Gods good Creatures,</hi> and a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> (I meane that <hi>Extemporary Interpretation</hi> of him which ſome few Moneths ſithence it pleaſed Your Honor to accept at my hands) now ſince he hath gotten about him better attyre and Language, hath emboldened him to make a Second ſhew of himſelfe, in hope that by Your <hi>Noble Protection</hi> he ſhall not onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer againſt the vniuſt and vnworthy <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations</hi> layd vpon him, but be Reſtored wholy to the poſſeſſion of his <hi>Original Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor:</hi> Namely; <hi>An Evangelical Prophet of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12429:4"/>Certainly he acknowlageth the large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Your <hi>Heart</hi> in vnderſtanding the things of <hi>God,</hi> The brightneſſe of Your <hi>Light</hi> in maters of Profoundeſt Search; and the <hi>Ardor</hi> of Your <hi>Spirit</hi> conſtantly aſpiring vnto <hi>Motions</hi> of the <hi>Pureſt Aire:</hi> Such <hi>Hearts</hi> onely can vnderſtand in theſe: Such <hi>Lights</hi> onely can diſcerne of them: And ſuch <hi>Spirits</hi> enioy the Comfort of theit <hi>Dew</hi> vſe: And becauſe there are ſo few of ſuch ones; therefore is it that this louely Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger hath beene ſo little ſet by among Men to their owne Reproofe and Loſſe inualua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. His demands are juſt, and the profit he tendreth to the Honorers of him <hi>ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,</hi> as appeareth by that which is here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed out of him. So that the goodneſſe of the cauſe it ſelfe remoueth all doubt, but that vnder your <hi>Excellencies</hi> countenance he ſhall aſſuredly finde plentifull regard, <hi>the Newneſſe of his preſent habit and ſpeech notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for my ſelfe; when I beheld (as I do <hi>dayly</hi>) the <hi>zelous</hi> and <hi>continual</hi> exerciſe of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety</hi> in your owne Perſon, the gracious pract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſe of <hi>Relligion</hi> in your <hi>family,</hi> the ſingular
<pb facs="tcp:12429:5"/>
good <hi>gouernment</hi> of your <hi>houſe,</hi> whereby the late <hi>dangerous times came not neere</hi> you, to touch you; nor any of yours (though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the middeſt of them). I cannot but be perſwaded, that your <hi>Noble</hi> and <hi>Pious ſpirit</hi> will vouchſafe to regard this my ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors (weake that they are) and fill vp the wants with the ſweetneſſe of your good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, which is wont not to reject any (proceeding from a <hi>ſingle heart</hi>) that is not altogether vnſauory.</p>
            <p>Wherefore my prayers vnto God for you (my Lord) are, that the <hi>Integrity</hi> of your wiſdome, your <hi>Relligious learning,</hi> your ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and your valor may crowne you with Honours and Richeſſe, and <hi>graces</hi> and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors both with God and Man, as if with full <hi>Sheffes</hi> the <hi>field</hi> which the Lord will haue bleſſed.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the vowes which do with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and delight vnſpeakable open the light of the Morning, and ſhut in the ſight of the Euening dayly, to your Honours trewly loyal ſeruant and <hi>Chapellan:</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>ROBERT SALTER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12429:5"/>
            <head>VINDICIAE DANIELIS.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Apocryphals in Generall.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>IRST, when I doe enter in to ſerious conſideration of the <hi>Sobriety</hi> of our fore-Fathers, that hauing receiued from their Elders a volume of <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> writings, would not bee want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to deliuer them ouer to their <hi>Poſterity</hi> in the <hi>ſame Number and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> they had receiued them; I cannot but approue their <hi>Pious Ingenuity,</hi> chooſing rather to ſubſcribe to their Elders in things not altogether <hi>intolerable,</hi> then to queſtion their <hi>diſcretion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in the Second place, when I behold the <hi>Synceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of men of our owne times, that will not admit the leaſt blaſt of <hi>Earthly Ayre</hi> to mixe it ſelfe with the <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> knowne to bee <hi>immediately</hi> breathed vnto vs by the <hi>Divine Spirit,</hi> I muſt needes admire their <hi>Religious inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity,</hi> that cannot indure any ſhew of <hi>Parity</hi> to finde place betwixt the things of God and of Men.</p>
               <p>Wherefore bleſſing them both in their ſeuerall Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; it is a <hi>Motion</hi> (I make no doubt) proceeding from the <hi>Spirit of Vnity and Truth,</hi> adored of them and vs all, that wee indeuour (by reconciling them what in vs ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) to injoy the benefit of both their <hi>Lights</hi> in <hi>common</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:12429:6"/>
with them; As wee rejoyce in the acknowledgement of <hi>Life in Communion</hi> with them.</p>
               <p>The Queſtion about which they differ is, That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as there are certaine writings deliuered vnto vs, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the bookes of the Firſt Couenant, partly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned as <hi>Members</hi> of ſome of thoſe bookes, and partly ſubjoyned as <hi>Entire</hi> workes in themſelues, and yet not found recorded in the <hi>ſame Character;</hi> whether they be to bee permitted to paſſe joyntly and promiſcuouſly as hitherto they haue done, or whether they ought at length to be <hi>diuorced</hi> as not lawfully brought together?</p>
               <p>Touching them all I haue not at this time to ſpeake; but leaue it to thoſe, whoſe libertie of time and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>State</hi> may ſolace themſelues in the louely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations there to bee found. For my part, (Firſt anſwering the exceptions brought againſt them in <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> ſuch as I haue found) I ſhall by the helpe of the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Grace</hi> diſcouer the <hi>Heauenly Myſteries</hi> implyed in ſome one Particular of them, if perhaps thereby, ſome other of them may finde the better entertainment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And thou ô Holy Spirit, which makeſt the light of truth to ſpring vp in our Hearts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſtl. 112.6.</note> 
                  <hi>out of the darkeneſſe of our Corrupt Nature, ſtrengthen mee by the heate of thy Loue, that the clouds of my ſinnes may bee ſo throughly diſſolued into ſhoures of contrite teares, that they neuer returne againe to hinder the ſight of thy comfort and conduct, this night of ignorance ſo powerfully praeiudicating vs in the things of God and our true happineſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One objection is that they are acknowledged on all ſides to bee writings <hi>Apocryphal;</hi> And therefore as ſome doe ſeeme to vnderſtand <hi>(ipſo nomine)</hi> not <hi>Canonicall:</hi> for as much as theſe Names are taken to bee ſo contrary in themſelues, as to be applyed to one and the ſame thing in one and the ſame reſpect is altogether impoſſible.</p>
               <p>Whereto I anſwer out of the <hi>Different</hi> meanings and vſes giuen to the name <hi>Apocryphal,</hi> which are found to be theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:12429:6"/>Firſt, this word <hi>Apocryphal</hi> indeede in a proper and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terall ſignification importeth <hi>[Hidden]</hi> or Remoued from our ſight, as it is ſaide [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] to hide the earth, when by ſayling farre into the Sea wee doe (as Sea-men vſe to ſpeake) bring land to wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the ſight of the Land is wholly taken from vs. And in this <hi>Paſſiue Nature</hi> it is after a <hi>figuratiue</hi> manner made conuertible with the word <hi>[Priuate,]</hi> which is to ſay <hi>[Sequeſtred]</hi> or hidden from publique vſe. So that taking the word <hi>[Canonical]</hi> to bee vſed for that which is made and ordained <hi>for publi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vſe,</hi> and is ſo receiued and vſed; in this ſenſe indeede theſe Names vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one and the ſame <hi>Subiect</hi> as is aboue ſaide are vtterly incompatible.</p>
               <p>But this word <hi>[Apocryphal]</hi> is found alſo capable of a <hi>Secundary</hi> intention. And that is by an <hi>Actiue</hi> ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to expreſſe an <hi>Excellencie</hi> of things, by which ſome haue in them a <hi>Preheminency</hi> of <hi>Brightneſſe</hi> and <hi>Illuminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or a <hi>ſuperiority</hi> of <hi>Dignity</hi> and victory in outward pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, whereby the <hi>preſence</hi> of others (of not ſo great <hi>Outward</hi> note) is obſcured; And ſo theſe become <hi>(La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebrae) Hyding places</hi> (as the word is alſo found vſed) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe others. And in this ſenſe theſe <hi>Apocryphals</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing according to the dead letter, but as the <hi>Shells,</hi> may haue for their kirnells maters of <hi>High and ſpirituall Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> encloſed and hidden in them, in ſort, that the Names of <hi>[Apocryphal]</hi> and <hi>[Myſticall]</hi> may be found in them of one and the ſame <hi>Aire</hi> and <hi>Senſe.</hi> And theſe <hi>Myſteries</hi> being found <hi>Conſonant</hi> and <hi>Analogicall</hi> to the <hi>Canon</hi> of the <hi>Sacred Scriptures,</hi> purchaſe thereby the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>[Canonical]</hi> together with them.</p>
               <p>For whereas according to the <hi>Literal</hi> context the <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories Apocryphal</hi> ſeeme to make mention of ſome paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges amongſt the <hi>Iewes,</hi> either in their <hi>Babilonian captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> or ſoone after, and ſo of no vſe nor <hi>Reference</hi> vnto <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> times: now if by a more <hi>illuminate</hi> ſearch they bee in <hi>Myſtery</hi> found to conuey vnto the <hi>preſent</hi> Church of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12429:7"/>
Chriſt ſuch <hi>Gratious ſpeculations,</hi> as either it cannot well want them, or at leaſt wiſe it be much holpen by them in <hi>their times</hi> and <hi>ſeaſons</hi> (which I doe verily beleeue our fore-Fathers did ſee, though the notice thereof, out of ſome ſpeciall worke of the <hi>Diuine prouidence</hi> haue not as yet beene imparted vnto vs:) Then will this applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the name <hi>[Apocryphal]</hi> bee ſufficient to vindicate them from the <hi>Aſperſions</hi> caſt on them by the <hi>Praeiudice</hi> of the former ſenſe.</p>
               <p>It is againe objected, that many <hi>falſities</hi> and doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, indecencies, and impoſſibilities are found in the Relations of their <hi>Hiſtories,</hi> and therefore not to bee admitted.</p>
               <p>This (for anſwer) is indeede confeſſed according to the <hi>letter</hi> of them to bee true; and I ſuppoſe many the like are to bee brought forth out of the <hi>Canonicals</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, which (as theſe) doe call for <hi>Spiritual</hi> eyes to diſcerne of them,<note place="margin">Ezeck. 4. Hoſ. 1. Luc. 16.</note> as <hi>Ezekiels</hi> bands and bread, and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeahs</hi> wife of fornications, the <hi>Rich mans</hi> charitie in Hell and ſuch like; So that to the one as well as to the other this ſeemeth to bee <hi>imputable.</hi> And therefore in theſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the eyes of fleſh and blood are of neceſſity to be clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and wee muſt ſubmit our ſelues wholly to bee led by the light of the <hi>Spirituall</hi> man, and ſtriue to acquiet our ſelues in the <hi>Myſteries</hi> of them, without nice ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Naturall</hi> reaſon.</p>
               <p>A farther Exception is, that becauſe they are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded within the <hi>Number</hi> of the <hi>Alphabeticall</hi> letters, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> as the <hi>Rabbines</hi> regiſter them to haue beene taken in <hi>Ezraes</hi> time, nor found in that <hi>holy tongue,</hi> nor admitted by <hi>Hebrewes</hi> old nor new, therefore they cannot haue beene breathed by <hi>Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For anſwer hereto, firſt I cannot but make vſe of the words of that good Father Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi> in an Epiſtle which hee writeth to Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> for inſtructions from him, as from <hi>his Elder.</hi> Hee there, vpon the words of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12429:7"/>
our Sauiour, <hi>[Bee yee not called Rabbi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>for one is your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter euen Chriſt]</hi> goeth on thus: <hi>Nec alius docuit Moſen, &amp;c.</hi> Neither was there (ſaith hee) any other, that taught <hi>Moſes</hi> by <hi>Iethro;</hi> nor <hi>Cornelius</hi> by <hi>Peter</hi> his Elder; nor <hi>Peter</hi> by <hi>Paul</hi> his younger. For by whom ſoeuer <hi>Truth</hi> is ſpoken, it is deliuered by the guift of him who is the <hi>Truth</hi> it ſelfe. And this ſame alſo and almoſt in the ſame words doth he repeate in his ſecond booke and 18. Chapter, touching the <hi>Doctrine of Chriſtianity,</hi> affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it is the dutie of euery <hi>good Chriſtian</hi> to know that whereſoeuer <hi>Trueth</hi> is found, (as well in <hi>Profane Authors</hi> as in <hi>Sacred</hi>) yet it is to bee referred to the breath of our Lord and Maiſter <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> from whoſe <hi>alone</hi> ſpirit all <hi>Trueth</hi> doth proceede. And ſo when in theſe, <hi>Truth</hi> is to bee found, whether after the <hi>Letter</hi> or in the <hi>Myſtery;</hi> then in reſpect of the <hi>fountaine</hi> whence it ſpringeth, it is to bee receiued for <hi>Certaine,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any <hi>Conditionate Admiſſion</hi> of <hi>[Magis &amp; Minus] more or leſſe</hi> trueth in the one of them, then in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I ſay, that <hi>Trueth</hi> being ſo found in them, it is not to bee beleeued,<note place="margin">Vnius cuiuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> linguae par eſt et eadem virtus, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>do par ſit &amp; eadem pietas. Cor. Agrip. de Cabala.</note> that the Spirit of God hath ſo confined it ſelfe, to any one <hi>Language</hi> of the Man <hi>more then other;</hi> that the <hi>Aire</hi> of the words being but <hi>Signes</hi> ſhould bring any <hi>credit</hi> to the <hi>Trueth,</hi> of the <hi>Things</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified. Or if any will needes haue, that it doth; why then may wee not rather beleeue, that for as much as the things of <hi>Trueth</hi> deliuered in theſe <hi>Apocryphals,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining principally to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> from that time ſhortly approaching, and not to the <hi>Moſaical</hi> now declining, were by the <hi>ſpeciall inſtinct</hi> of <hi>Gods Spirit,</hi> dictated in the Mouth of the <hi>Pen-men,</hi> in ſuch language of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as was ordeined to bee the inſtrument of conueighing the <hi>Doctrine of Chriſt,</hi> at hand, to bee reuealed to all the world?<note place="margin">Iſa. 28.11. 1. Cor. 14.21.</note> Therein to the very <hi>Letter</hi> ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling the Prophecie, as the Apoſtle rendreth it, <hi>[with other tongues, and with other lippes will I ſpeake vnto this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12429:8"/>
people.]</hi> And euen in that it ſelfe, intimating to the people of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that as they were now (by the pleaſure of God) made ſubject to the <hi>Gentiles in body;</hi> ſo they ſhould in <hi>minde</hi> ſubmit themſelues, to bee ruled by that forme of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> which was in the <hi>Gentiles lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,</hi> to bee made <hi>Authentical</hi> vnto <hi>them.</hi> And this may wee bee the rather induced to beleeue, in that wee finde the firſt miraculous confirmation of the <hi>Euangelical Doctrine of Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 2.</note> after his <hi>full Glorification,</hi> to bee in this ſame kinde: namely, the <hi>Sanctification and Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Languages</hi> vnto that <hi>Miniſtery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet, notwithſtanding all that hath beene ſaide in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of theſe <hi>Apocryphals,</hi> I doe neuertheleſſe humbly deſire ſo to bee vnderſtood, that it is farre from mee, ſo much as in the leaſt ſhadow of my thoughts <hi>ſeparately</hi> to <hi>parallel</hi> them to the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> (which haue from the <hi>beginning,</hi> and euermore beene by the whole Church acknowledged <hi>Canonicall</hi> and <hi>Authentique,</hi>) whether for <hi>Meaſure of ſpirit,</hi> or <hi>Light of iudgement,</hi> or <hi>Authoritie of bynding power,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>or finally, for ſufficiencie of Doctrine [to make the man of God perfect, &amp;c.]</hi> Yet may it bee no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement to thoſe <hi>pure fires</hi> of <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> that theſe <hi>Apocryphals</hi> be to them taken <hi>[Coniunctim,]</hi> as the <hi>Golden Pot,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 16.</note> to the <hi>Manna</hi> laide vp therein; or as the <hi>Vehicula</hi> which Phyſicians doe vſe in the applying of their <hi>Medicines,</hi> whereby their <hi>richeſt Antidotes</hi> are brought to a more <hi>vniuerſall benefite,</hi> for the whole <hi>body</hi> of the <hi>Man;</hi> or as the <hi>steely Armour</hi> of the Lode-ſtone, which is altogether impotent of <hi>its owne ſeperate</hi> ſtrength, to worke <hi>Magneticall Attraction;</hi> Howbeit, <hi>fitted</hi> duely to that inualuably precious <hi>Gem,</hi> doth by <hi>copulation, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply</hi> the virtues thereof, to diſpart it ſelfe into a much <hi>greater Orbe,</hi> and with more <hi>powerfull rayes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How juſtly this that hath beene ſaide, is applyable to theſe <hi>Apocryphals,</hi> I leaue to the Aeſtimate of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts which haue laboured in ſome parts of them, <hi>not vnthriftily;</hi> their worke is their <hi>crowne,</hi> and the <hi>Sterres</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:12429:8"/>
thereof ſhall be multiplyed dayly, <hi>vnto the day of Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Retribution.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Apocryphals of <hi>Daniel.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat which by mee hath hitherto beene ſaide, ſerueth firſt, to remoue the <hi>Obiections</hi> which <hi>praeiudice</hi> had laide to the charge of thoſe <hi>Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> writings; which doubtleſſe, had neuer beene ſo <hi>Conſtantly, Reuerently,</hi> and <hi>Relligiouſly</hi> preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, in <hi>one and the ſame</hi> cloſet with the <hi>Sacred Scriptures,</hi> had not the <hi>Diuine Prouidence</hi> ſpecially wrought, and beene pleaſed to ſhine forth therein. And ſo in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place, this ſerueth alſo, to purchaſe a <hi>reſpectiue Attention,</hi> to that which is therein contained; and that we labour and vſe meanes, that the ſame may be <hi>Reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> vnto vs, in regard of the great <hi>benefite reſulting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſpeciall part, I haue choſen for the preſent to ſpeake vnto, is the <hi>Auctary of Daniel.</hi> Which appeareth to me, whether for the <hi>neceſſity of knowledge</hi> of the <hi>Trewth,</hi> implyed in it; either for the <hi>Amplitude of th' Extent</hi> of it; or laſtly, or the <hi>Height of the Spirit,</hi> by which it was dictated, to aduow vnto it ſelfe place in the former ranke.</p>
               <p>Firſt therefore, whereas wee finde the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> adfixed vnto it; whether it be <hi>literally</hi> after the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> thereof, the Pen-man of the <hi>Canonicall Prophecie:</hi> Certainly, the <hi>matter</hi> therein contained, doth acquite it ſelfe, not vnworthy the name of ſo <hi>Glorious</hi> a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. Or if it bee <hi>Parabolically,</hi> according to the <hi>Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance</hi> of the <hi>Subiect,</hi> to that of the former. The <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> of the Name, and <hi>Adiection</hi> of it vnto that other, doth no way impaire the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>ſelfe-ſufficiencie,</hi> of that <hi>Gracious Canonical Prophecie:</hi> As will appeare by that which followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:12429:9"/>But what if in a <hi>Myſtery,</hi> we vnderſtand the Name of <hi>Daniel,</hi> giuen vnto it from the <hi>Abſtract</hi> of the Name it ſelfe without any <hi>Reference</hi> to any perſon in <hi>Concrete?</hi> And ſo the Name intimating the Manner of Gods work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his <hi>iudgements,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Daniel. <hi>1.</hi> The iudgement of God. Or, God is iudge.</note> according to thoſe times in the which the Seueral parts of this <hi>Prophecy</hi> were to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled?</p>
               <p>In trewth when I behold the gracious <hi>vnity</hi> in Spirit, betwixt the workes of <hi>God</hi> of this kinde, in the times before this <hi>Prophecy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 32. Iud. 2. 2 Sam. 24. Pſa. 90.106. Ioel. 2. Iona. 2. Luc. 18. 2. Pet. 2. 1. Tim. 1.</note> as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaketh of them, <hi>[The Lord will iudge his People, and be compaſſionate over his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants,]</hi> And as we finde it often repeated by the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> ſucceſſiuely; and in the times as they enſued after this <hi>Prophecy,</hi> as they are ſpoken of by our Sauiour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his Apoſtles after him; I am wholly poſſeſſed with Perſuaſion and ample Aſſurance, that this Name of <hi>Daniel</hi> giuen to this <hi>Auctary,</hi> is Principally (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the letter,) <hi>Apocryphal;</hi> that is to ſay, A couert and <hi>ſhell</hi> wherein the Nature of <hi>Gods Iudgements</hi> then to enſue, were <hi>Myſtically</hi> encloſed.</p>
               <p>For this <hi>Auctary,</hi> albeit that it is found diſperſed into <hi>diuers</hi> Sections, as Namely, the <hi>Additional</hi> to the <hi>third Chapter</hi> of the <hi>Canonical Prophecy,</hi> and the <hi>XIII</hi> and <hi>XIV chapters,</hi> as they are added to the end of the <hi>Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Prophecy:</hi> yet by the <hi>Coherence</hi> and dependency of them one on the other, it appeareth to be one <hi>continent Prophecy;</hi> reporting in <hi>Angelical Language</hi> the State of the <hi>Church</hi> and Faithfull, from thoſe times to the End of times; vnder the Type of the <hi>Babilonian Captiuity</hi> of the Iewes, the onely faithfull Church at that time manifeſt in the world. And diſtributeth it ſelfe into IIII. diſtinct Paſſages or Periods very regardable. Namely.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Dan. 3.</note>I. <hi>A DIVINE PROTECTION of three Religious young men in a fiery Fornace.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Dan. 13.</note>II. <hi>A IVDICIALL DELIVERY of a chaſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12429:9"/>
wife diſtreſſed by Calumny of</hi> II. <hi>old Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cators.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>An INGENIOVS CONFVTATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON and Conviction of an IDOLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TROVS CVLTVRE.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dan. 14.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>IV. <hi>A IVST RETRIBVTION executed on a tumultuous People,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vbi.</hi> 5.</note> 
                     <hi>BRVTISHLY conſpiring againſt their FAITHFVLL RVLER ſent them from GOD.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>And into ſuch IV. <hi>Periods</hi> are the <hi>Times</hi> of the world thence enſuing exactly reduced, as appeareth by the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of other <hi>Prophecies Canonical.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The firſt Period is of the Martyrdome of three young men.</head>
               <p>VVHerein the firſt <hi>Circumſtance</hi> is of theſe III. <hi>Noble</hi> men,<note place="margin">And they walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the flame.</note> which if they bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>figuratiuely [A Definite number for an Indefinite,]</hi> Then is it to bee taken for that <hi>competency</hi> of witneſſes, that ſhould ſpring vp with one voice, confeſſing the <hi>Trewth</hi> of God in his <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> and <hi>Prouidence, That</hi> in the mids of all the <hi>Tumults</hi> and <hi>vexations</hi> of the world, it is directed wholly to the worke of his <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Loue,</hi> to the <hi>Man</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by his <hi>Spirit</hi> comforting and confirming them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, if wee conſider them <hi>Typically,</hi> it is to bee taken for the three <hi>Lawes Natural, Moſaical,</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelical;</hi> which in the mids of all the <hi>Frowardneſſes</hi> of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12429:10"/>
worldlings,<note place="margin">Al the workes of the Lord bleſſe ye the Lord, &amp;c.</note> doe by a ſweete and melodious <hi>vnicent,</hi> publiſh the prayſes of the <hi>Creator,</hi> to bee teſtified by the <hi>voice</hi> of the <hi>whole</hi> frame of the <hi>Creature,</hi> and <hi>parts</hi> thereof.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, if taken <hi>Myſtically,</hi> it putteth vs in minde of the preſent and ready <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> wee injoy in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the <hi>Manhod</hi> of God, by his <hi>Offices</hi> of <hi>Prince, Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Prophet,</hi> in the <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> of his <hi>Prouidence</hi> ouer all his creatures, for our ſeruice and good. In aſſurance whereof, hee doth not faile to rayſe vp vnto his <hi>Church</hi> in all <hi>Tentations</hi> and <hi>Preſſures</hi> faithfull ones of all theſe ſorts, namely, <hi>Princes, Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Prophets,</hi> from time to time <hi>repreſentatiue</hi> of <hi>himſelfe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ap. 1.</note> walking in the middeſt of it.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, if taken after the the manner of <hi>Parabolical Hiſtory,</hi> it doth report vnto vs, vnder the <hi>Notation</hi> of the names of theſe three young Men, the threefold differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Men, as they are deſcended from their firſt fathers af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>Deluge.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iapheth</hi> Enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Chananiah,</hi> Gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tified with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Europe</hi> wholly, The greater part of <hi>Aſia: Indies,</hi> Eaſt and Weſt: South-Pole Lands.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Shem.</hi> The name. <hi>Azariah.</hi> The helpe of God. <hi>Cham.</hi> Burnt with heate <hi>Miſhael.</hi> God is with-drawn.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Chananiah</hi> anſwering to the name of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth</hi> the eldeſt brother, whom (according to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie</hi> of his Father <hi>Noah</hi> vpon his name) it ſhould pleaſe <hi>God</hi> to <hi>Gratifie</hi> with <hi>Largeneſſe</hi> of Earthly <hi>Dominion,</hi> (namely, the <hi>greateſt</hi> part of the whole <hi>Habitable,</hi>) and to coinherite with the <hi>Bleſſed Shem</hi> in the <hi>Heauenly Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Azariah</hi> anſwering to <hi>Shem</hi> the ſecond brother, who was alſo (according to his name) to bee as the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Helpe</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> vnto the <hi>Generations</hi> of both his <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Miſhael</hi> anſwering to <hi>Cham</hi> the youngeſt, who (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his name alſo) was by the <hi>burning</hi> of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers diſpleaſure <hi>Excomunicate</hi> from any <hi>Society,</hi> and confined to a <hi>ſeruitude</hi> vnder the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Shem</hi> and <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth,</hi> whereby <hi>God</hi> might be thought to haue <hi>withdrawne</hi> himſelfe from him.</p>
               <p>Theſe in the mouth of <hi>Azariah</hi> the holy <hi>Shem,</hi> vnto whom the bleſſing (as is aboue ſaide) was moſt pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12429:10"/>
alloted in his iſſue the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> are ſummoned to beare witneſſe, to the praiſes of <hi>Gods,</hi> who had beene alwaies a preſent <hi>Helpe</hi> to himſelfe, and would now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue into <hi>fauour</hi> his elder Brother <hi>Iapheth,</hi> as hee had promiſed; and alſo returne and draw vnto him his yongeſt, whereof the forlorne ſeede of <hi>Cham</hi> had no <hi>Argument</hi> of Hope.</p>
               <p>Which applicataon is to me the more approoued, in that <hi>Azariah</hi> repreſenting the People of the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſprung from <hi>Shem,</hi> (and chiefe Author of this holy <hi>Hymne;</hi>) doth name himſelfe in the ſecond place onely, after <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naniah,</hi> (his brother <hi>Iaphet</hi>) elder then himſelfe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Nature, though inferiour in calling accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Bleſſing.</hi> And this ſong fulfilled in the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who being now againe brought into a <hi>fornace</hi> of Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity vnder the <hi>Babilonians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 81.</note> as they had before beene vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> are made the Preachers of <hi>Gods Trewth</hi> by their <hi>Diſperſion</hi> throughout the world. And the Nations thereby prepared and brought more <hi>flexible</hi> to entertaine the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of their <hi>Reconcilement</hi> to <hi>God</hi> by <hi>Christ</hi> ſhortly to be reuealed.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, and laſtly, <hi>Prophetically</hi> it beareth thus; That whereas the <hi>Nation</hi> of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> the onely <hi>now-viſible Church</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> were to be as the comnon threſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing floore, or fornace of Affliction, wherein the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples round about them ſhould expreſſe their furyes: yet the trew <hi>Iewes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> whoſe <hi>Circumciſion is not Outwardly of the fleſh, according to the Letter, but inwardly of the Heart, and according to the Spirit;</hi> ſhould be comforted by the <hi>Senſible Notice</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> gratious care ouer them in their Reliefe from People of all ſorts; whether of the <hi>Iewes</hi> in <hi>Azariah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Azariah. Ananiah.</note> Publique Profeſſors of <hi>God</hi> according to his written word, or of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in <hi>Chananiah;</hi> ſuch as (though far of) yet had ſome Light of the Trewth, wherein they reioyced themſelues, and ſhewed <hi>Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> vnto the <hi>Iewes</hi> the bringers of it vnto them; by the benefite of whoſe inclination, the <hi>Iewes</hi> were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12429:11"/>
freely their <hi>Sabbaths</hi> and <hi>Iubilees,</hi> and other <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Rites</hi> among foreine Nations, and vncircumciſed People where they were ſcattered,<note place="margin">Gozan. Chalac, &amp; Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor. <hi>2</hi> R <hi>17.</hi> Act. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> euen as far as <hi>Goeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, Colchis</hi> and <hi>Iberia,</hi> and the inland parts of <hi>Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> moſt remote from their owne Countrey: and (as the bleſſed <hi>Martyr St. Stephen</hi> ſaith,) beyond <hi>Babilon.</hi> Or laſtly,<note place="margin">Miſhael.</note> of thoſe Libertines and <hi>Pagans</hi> in <hi>Miſhael;</hi> ſuch as for their <hi>profaneneſſe</hi> hauing beene by the hand of <hi>God</hi> ſmitten into furies with <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> are compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to proclaime their owne ſhame, and <hi>Gods glory,</hi> though ſtill perſiſting <hi>Incendiaries</hi> to the whole world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Then Azariah ſtood forth and prayed, &amp; ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his mouth in the midſt of the fire. <hi>1. Pet. 1.7. &amp; 4.12.</hi>
                  </note>The <hi>ſecond Circumſtance</hi> is of a <hi>Fiary fornace,</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenteth vnto vs, that fire whereof the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> maketh mention; <hi>Originally</hi> poynting to the words of <hi>Moſes, [His law to them was a fire]</hi> which for their <hi>try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> the faithfull were to paſſe, that they might come forth <hi>precious veſſels</hi> for their <hi>Lords ſeruice,</hi> whoſe comming to <hi>Bridals,</hi> by his <hi>Incarnation</hi> and <hi>Humiliation</hi> did now haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, and they earneſtly wiſh and waite for.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut. 33.2.</hi> The Kings ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants that had caſt them in, cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not to make the ouen hot with Naptha, &amp;c.</note>The <hi>third Circumſtance</hi> is the <hi>Materials</hi> of the <hi>fire, Naptha, Pitch, Tow,</hi> and <hi>Vine-twigs,</hi> which doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne vnto vs, that the Countrey where theſe were found, moſt kindly breed and manured, were to bee the moſt proper places of theſe <hi>Tryals</hi> and <hi>Combuſtions,</hi> and thoſe were <hi>Babilonia, Perſia, Chaldaea, Syria, Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicia, Aſia minor,</hi> and <hi>Aegypt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Angel of the Lord ſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t the flame of the fire out of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace. <hi>Gen. 3.</hi>
                  </note>The <hi>fourth Circumſtance</hi> is, of the <hi>flame</hi> beaten <hi>forth</hi> of the <hi>Fornace,</hi> which is the <hi>Combuſtions</hi> that the world was then ſhortly to bee caſt into, which (as it was in the <hi>Beginning</hi> a <hi>Seraphim</hi> to the Tree of Life, <hi>ſeparating</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt it and <hi>The Man fallen</hi> from his <hi>Perfection;</hi> ſo now) was to as many as by <hi>faith</hi> were reſtored to their firſt <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ex. 13. Deut. 1.</note> made a <hi>Partition</hi> (as the <hi>Pillar</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in their departure out of <hi>Aegypt</hi>) &amp; a <hi>Lode-ſtarre</hi> of <hi>Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> (as it was to them in the <hi>wilderneſſe</hi>) to as many as will rejoyce in the Light thereof; but a <hi>ſword</hi> conſuming
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12429:11"/>
the vnbeleeuers (as was that from Heauen vpon <hi>Sedom,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 19. 2. Reg. 1.</note> and that vpon the two Captaines and their troupes that came againſt <hi>Elijah,</hi>) while in the meane ſpace the <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants</hi> of God in the midſt of theſe <hi>Combuſtions,</hi> walke <hi>Inuiſible</hi> to the world, (as the <hi>Aire</hi> by <hi>Inflammation</hi> is made <hi>Intranſparent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Not to be ſeen through. Zac. 2.</note> God making it to them a <hi>fiery</hi> wall of <hi>Infinite extent</hi> for the <hi>Receptacle</hi> of his <hi>Church,</hi> an <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable Rampart</hi> againſt them that are <hi>without,</hi> and a <hi>Gracious Communion</hi> of his <hi>Holyneſſe</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> by his <hi>conſtant preſence</hi> among them. Thus to them is it a <hi>fire,</hi> not to <hi>burne,</hi> but to <hi>Illuminate, Purge</hi> and <hi>ſanctifie</hi> them, but to the others, conſuming and deſtroying.</p>
               <p>The <hi>fifth Circumſtance</hi> is, of the XLIX.<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>The flame went out of the fornace</hi> 49 <hi>cubits. And it brake forth &amp; burnt thoſe Chal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deans that it found by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace.</hi> Dan. 9.</p>
                     <p>A Decade is the number of <hi>ten,</hi> as we vſe to ſay A couple, or a brace for two, or a leaſh for three.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Cubits</hi> of the <hi>fires</hi> rage, which is the <hi>Period</hi> of thoſe outragious times; either anſwering to the LXX. weekes of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical Prophecie,</hi> euery Cubit fulfilling a <hi>Decade</hi> of yeares, from the time of the commandement giuen, for the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne</hi> out of <hi>Captiuity,</hi> as the <hi>Prophet</hi> had limited; Either elſe it is a <hi>Decade</hi> of <hi>Iubilies,</hi> in the end whereof, the <hi>trew Iubilie</hi> (whereof all the former were but <hi>Types</hi>) ſhould bee celebrated, by the grant of Liberty from the <hi>Rigor</hi> of <hi>the Moſaical Law and Ceremonies,</hi> and from <hi>Sin, Death,</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> (vnto which onely Enemies <hi>the man</hi> was obnoxious.) And this <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Manumiſſion</hi> to bee graunted <hi>Indefinitely</hi> and without <hi>Limitation,</hi> to as many as did content themſelues, in the <hi>ſober</hi> and <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient</hi> expectation and <hi>ſalutation</hi> of it, yet ſo far off.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Jubile</hi> is called the <hi>fiftieth yeare,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Leuit. 25.</note> will make no <hi>difference.</hi> For the computation of <hi>Iewes</hi> and other thoſe <hi>Eaſterly Nations,</hi> being <hi>[Incluſiuè]</hi> accompting both the termes, as is the manner of <hi>Phyſitians</hi> in their <hi>Paroxyſmes</hi> of ſharpe diſeaſes, (whereby appeareth from whence they are to acknowledge the <hi>Propagation</hi> of that Learning), And the computation of the <hi>Greekes</hi> (in whoſe tongue this our <hi>Prophecie</hi> is found written) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>[Excluſiuè]</hi> leauing out one of the <hi>Termes,</hi> it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth out, that one and the ſame yeare in the <hi>Compute</hi> of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12429:12"/>
Time, commeth to bee the fiftieth yeare vnto the <hi>Iewes,</hi> which vnto the <hi>Grecians</hi> and other <hi>Weſtern Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> is but the fortie ninth. As appeareth by this <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gram.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure>
                  <head>IVBILE.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <hi>A figure of ſeuen ſides, euery ſide conteining ſeuen yeares for the</hi> Iehudean <hi>Sabbath of yeares, which maketh forty nine yeares, In ſort, that the firſt of the firſt Babbath, being reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned alſo for the last of the</hi> Iubilean Period (<hi>as it is</hi> Leuit. 25.) <hi>maketh vp the full number of fiftie for the yeare of</hi> Iubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le <hi>vnto the former, and the firſt yeare of the Sabbath follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:12429:12"/>
                  <head>The Accompliſhment.</head>
                  <p>FOr from the time of the <hi>Returne</hi> vpon the <hi>Going forth</hi> of the <hi>word,</hi> vnto the <hi>Conſummation determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for the ouerſpreading Abomination,</hi> were trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blous times through the whole world: As the <hi>Harmony</hi> of <hi>Annals</hi> do ſhew; In the which <hi>God</hi> did not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding raiſe vp from time to time for the Comfort of his Church, a <hi>competent number of witneſſes</hi> to his <hi>Trewth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>(This word was not that giuen by <hi>Cyrus, (Ezra.</hi> 1.1.)<note place="margin">This Note (though not all ſo proper in the matter) I could not omit, for loue of the gracious medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation it ocaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth.</note> which was about the 29. yeare of the <hi>Epocha</hi> or <hi>Style</hi> of the <hi>Perſian Monarchy,</hi> and the 222. yeare of the <hi>Building</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> which fel in the time of <hi>Tarquinius Superbus</hi> the <hi>laſt</hi> King of <hi>Rome</hi> about 530. yeares <hi>before the word became Man.</hi> But the <hi>Going forth of the word (Daniel</hi> 9 25.) by the Miniſtery of <hi>Haggai</hi> and <hi>Zachariah</hi> the <hi>Prophets,</hi> vnder <hi>Darius Nothus</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Syrus;</hi> which was aboue 100. yeares after the former; Namely, about the 137. yeare of the <hi>Perſian Aera;</hi> the 330. yeare of <hi>Rome built,</hi> 420. yeares before <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the <hi>Prince;</hi> and about the <hi>firſt Reducing</hi> of this our <hi>Albion</hi> into a <hi>Monarchy</hi> by the <hi>Great Mulmutius</hi> father to the valiant <hi>Belinus</hi> and <hi>Bremus:</hi> where we haue to obſerue that the <hi>Foundation</hi> of the <hi>Politique State</hi> of this our Land, beginneth with the <hi>Foundation</hi> of the <hi>Second Temple,</hi> (the <hi>Type</hi> of the calling of the <hi>Gentiles</hi>) laid by our <hi>Prophets aboue praiſed.</hi> As afterward, <hi>the full comming in</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> and <hi>Submiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to the <hi>Goſpell</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> by <hi>Publique Conſenſe</hi> was <hi>(firſt of all Nations)</hi> begun by the <hi>Politique State</hi> of this Land vnder our <hi>Chriſtian King Lucius,</hi> before the firſt generall Conuerſion of the <hi>Romane Empire</hi> vnder their <hi>Emperour Conſtantine</hi> neere 130 yeares.)</p>
                  <p>Firſt among the <hi>Iewes;</hi> As of <hi>Rulers,</hi> ſuch were <hi>Zerub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babel,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12429:13"/>
Tirſhatha,</hi> the valiant <hi>Maccabees,</hi> &amp;c. As of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> ſuch were <hi>Ezra, Iehoſchuah, Iadduah</hi> that turned the Heart of <hi>Alexander</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> from demolliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Ieruſalem, Eleazarus</hi> to whom <hi>Ptolome</hi> ſent for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters, <hi>Simon</hi> the <hi>Juſt, Onias</hi> the <hi>Holy,</hi> &amp;c. As of <hi>Prophets,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 1. Luc. 3.</note> ſuch were <hi>Haggar, Zachary, Malachy;</hi> and that <hi>Sterry Streame</hi> from <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> to the <hi>Virgin Mother</hi> as the <hi>Euangeliſts</hi> doe record them.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, among the <hi>Gentiles</hi> as of <hi>pious Proſelites</hi> and <hi>Proficients;</hi> ſuch as were thoſe noble <hi>Pythagoreans, Sybills,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tit. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Sages</hi> of <hi>Greece,</hi> and other <hi>Phyloſophers, Hyſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and <hi>Prophets,</hi> (ſo doth the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> call their <hi>Poets;</hi>) And thoſe (not inferior in learning to the beſt of them) <hi>Druides</hi> of this our <hi>Heauen-named Albion,</hi> (I weigh not fables,) <hi>Ptolomaus Philadelphus</hi> and <hi>Ariſtaus</hi> his fauorite, to whome the whole world is indebted for hauing beene inſtruments of bringing the <hi>Diuine Oracles</hi> to ſpeake to vs in our <hi>owne</hi> tongues, and others of whome we finde large teſtimonies in that moſt diligent and <hi>truſty Annaliſt Ioſephus,</hi> and elſe where.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, among profane <hi>Libertines,</hi> ſuch as were <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the <hi>Great, Antiochus</hi> the <hi>Great, Seleucus Nicanor,</hi> and others both <hi>Aſiatiques</hi> and <hi>Africans, Grecians</hi> and <hi>Romans,</hi> whereto beareth Suffrage the Inſcription of that <hi>Altar</hi> in <hi>Athens:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>[To the vnknowne God]</hi> and the common ſpeach of thoſe dayes <hi>[of the world to come]</hi> which the <hi>Poet</hi> profanely enough wreſteth in his verſe.</p>
                  <q>Magnus ab integro Seclorum naſcitur ordo.</q>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Virg. Pollio.</note>All theſe I ſay, and many moe from time to time, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the comming of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> were vnto the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the mids of thoſe <hi>Combuſtions,</hi> as the ſtill ſmall voice to <hi>Elijah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>1. Reg. 19.</hi> And the Angell made like a moiſt hiſsing wind in the midſt of the fornace. <hi>2. Macc. 6. &amp; 7.</hi>
                     </note> refreſhing their wearied <hi>Spirits,</hi> with the ſolace they tooke in the <hi>Expectation</hi> of their <hi>Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;</hi> though to the world they ſeemed ineuitably embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with flames no leſſe tormenting, then were thoſe conſtant <hi>Martyrs, Eleazar</hi> the Scribe, and the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> and her ſeuen ſonnes in the fornace of <hi>Epiphanes:</hi>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:12429:13"/>
But this was (I ſay) vnto <hi>them</hi> a refuge from greater euills; and to the <hi>world,</hi> and to them that were <hi>without,</hi> a gulfe of deſtruction,<note place="margin">The flame burſt forth and burns thoſe that is found by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace.</note> as appeareth by the continuall deſolations betwixt the <hi>Perſians</hi> and <hi>Graecians, Seleucidans,</hi> and <hi>Lagidans,</hi> vntill they all at length, fall before the <hi>Romans,</hi> as was foretold by our <hi>Prophet</hi> in his <hi>Canonical</hi> meſſage.</p>
                  <p>And now is the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> come,<note place="margin">The Angel of the Lord went downe into the fornace with them that were with Azarias.</note> and though nothing be found in him, yet muſt hee enter into the ſame <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace,</hi> no leſſe <hi>[Paſſiaè]</hi> to ſuffer with them; then <hi>[Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatiuè]</hi> to take the force of the fire from them. And ſo muſt the reſt of all thoſe holy veſſels, his <hi>Confeſſors</hi> follow as they did, vntill the time of theſe <hi>Deſolating fires</hi> accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, as is aboue ſhewed. And ſo this <hi>Period</hi> end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with the <hi>expiration</hi> of the <hi>Moſaical bondage;</hi> to the obedience whereof, theſe holy witneſſes were engaged, euen to the <hi>Death,</hi> and were now to riſe againe, and come forth to the life of <hi>Euangelical Liberty.</hi> The vtmoſt <hi>limitation</hi> of which their <hi>ſtay</hi> in this <hi>fornace,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke 21.</note> our Sauiour deſigneth vnto them to bee <hi>[the beleaguering of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.]</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond <hi>Period</hi> is of the <hi>chaſt wife.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT was very fit that there ſhould bee a large diſtance betwixt the <hi>Relating</hi> of the former <hi>paſſage,</hi> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the three <hi>Noble</hi> young Men <hi>martyred,</hi> and this next inſuing. For there was a long courſe of <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currents</hi> to bee accompliſhed betwixt them; Euen ſo much as was to take vp <hi>fortie nine Cubits,</hi> or ſeuentie weekes of time, which (as was ſhewed before) were thoſe foure hundred and ninety yeares, in which all the <hi>Prophecies</hi> enſuing that part (namely the <hi>third Chapter</hi> of the <hi>Canonicall Prophecy,</hi> whereto our former <hi>Progreſſe</hi> is ſubioyned) were to be fulfilled. And ſo the <hi>Connexion</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:12429:14"/>
of theſe Paſſages which now follow, to ſet an end to the whole <hi>Prophecy.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>In this <hi>Period</hi> of the <hi>Chaſt wife.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> THe firſt <hi>Circumſtance</hi> is of the <hi>Place</hi> named <hi>Babilon:</hi> Not the <hi>firſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>There dwels in Babylon a man called Ioacim, &amp;c. Babilon.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. Pſa. 137. Iſa. 13. Ier. 50. &amp; 51. Ap. 13.</note> for it was long ſithence deſolated in the flames of the <hi>former Period,</hi> and made an <hi>Extemplary Confuſion</hi> to al the Enemies of <hi>God</hi> and his People, as it was foretold, and commanded by the <hi>Prophets.</hi> And al the <hi>Saints</hi> of <hi>God</hi> were called out of it long ſithence.</p>
                  <p>But it is of the <hi>Second</hi> now, by this time ſtanding and growne <hi>great,</hi> by the ſpoiles of all the world beſides; And which was to begin a <hi>New Captiuity</hi> of the <hi>People of God,</hi> and to make a <hi>New Depraedation</hi> of the <hi>Church of God,</hi> and to ſet vp a <hi>new Confuſion,</hi> out of the <hi>Ruines</hi> of the old. So then this chaſt wife muſt be put to her Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation in <hi>Babilon</hi> the <hi>NEW.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>And he tooke a wife named Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanna. Suſanna.</hi> A Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Cant. 2. Ap. 17. 1. Reg. 7. <hi>Iehotakim.</hi> The eſtabliſhment of God. 2. Cor. 1.</note>The <hi>ſecond Circumſtance</hi> is, of the <hi>Perſon, [The Church]</hi> which is firſt deſcribed by her <hi>Name [Suſanna]</hi> A <hi>Lilly.</hi> For ſo doth God decipher his <hi>Church</hi> in the world <hi>[As the Lilly among the thornes,] Suſanna</hi> a chaſt wife in <hi>Babilon</hi> the mother of <hi>Harlotry.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> by the name of her Husband <hi>[Iehoiakim.]</hi> The <hi>Pillar</hi> which <hi>God</hi> hath eſtabliſhed, and not Man. For <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>ſpouſe</hi> of his <hi>Church,</hi> in whom God hath ratified all the purpoſes and promiſes of his <hi>loue</hi> vnto the <hi>man</hi> by an <hi>irrefragable Couenant</hi> of <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> And <hi>Hee</hi> taketh <hi>her</hi> to wife; for Chriſt loued his <hi>first.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The daughter of Helkiah. Helkiah. <hi>Gods-Lot. Eph. 1.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> by the name of her Father; <hi>Helkiah,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>The portion</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> For God had <hi>choſen</hi> vs to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in <hi>Chriſt</hi> before the <hi>foundation</hi> of the world, that we ſhould bee <hi>holy</hi> and without blame before him in <hi>loue.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly</hi> by her <hi>preſence, Shee</hi> is very <hi>faire,</hi> for <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath preſented her to himſelfe <hi>Glorious,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A very faire woman. <hi>Eph. 5.</hi>
                     </note> without <hi>ſpot</hi> or wrinckle, <hi>Holy and without blame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fifthly,</hi> by the <hi>Regularity</hi> of her <hi>Education.</hi> Shee is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12429:14"/>
by her righteous Parents bred <hi>Religiouſly;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">And one that feared God. Her father and mother alſo were godly people, &amp; taught her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording &amp;c. <hi>Pſ. 119.</hi> Now Ioacim was a great rich ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Col. 2. 1. Tim. 4.</hi> Vrbem fecisti. qui prius Orbis erat. Rutil.</note> For it is the word of God that muſt bee the <hi>[Lanthorne to our feete,]</hi> without which, the <hi>wiſdome</hi> of the man is <hi>folly,</hi> and his righteouſneſſe, <hi>prouocation</hi> and <hi>vnexcuſableneſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lastly,</hi> her Husband is very Rich and Honourable, for in Chriſt are all the <hi>Treaſures</hi> of the <hi>Deity;</hi> and the <hi>Godly</hi> haue the <hi>Promiſes</hi> of <hi>this Life</hi> and of the <hi>Life to come.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So then, here haue we a perfect <hi>Purtrait</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> as our Sauiour at his departure from the <hi>Iewes,</hi> the place of his earthly abode, had <hi>ſequeſtred</hi> her to himſelfe, from amids the world of the <hi>Gentiles (the new Babilon)</hi> for his owne and <hi>Onely</hi> beloued, and ſhee a <hi>chaſt wife,</hi> faithfull and <hi>loyal</hi> to her deere Lord and Husband, whoſe <hi>onely</hi> voice ſhee followeth.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>third Circumſtance</hi> is, of two <hi>Luxurious Iudges,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The two Elders ſeeing her, haue a luſt vnto her</note>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/>
the one of them, the <hi>Idolatrous Paganiſme</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> not yet conuerted to the <hi>faith</hi> of Chriſt: the other, the <hi>obſtinate ſuperstitiouſneſſe</hi> of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> ſtill perſiſting in hardneſſe of heart and vnbeleife, concerning any of the <hi>promiſes</hi> of God, that they ſhould bee accompliſhed in our Lord and Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus. And that theſe are the perſons which they repreſent doth very liuely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the ſeuerall <hi>Detections</hi> brought againſt them in the mouth of our <hi>Myſtical Daniel (The iudgement of God)</hi> though but a childe; For the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> of God in Chriſt, was yet but as in the <hi>nonage</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. Firſt, Againſt the <hi>former</hi> is brought forth the ſame burden that is by the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> laide vpon the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> for their <hi>vnthrifty Ingratitude</hi> towards God,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> namely <hi>vnrighteouſneſſe, vnmercifulneſſe, vnnaturalneſſe,</hi> &amp;c. And in the next place, againſt the later is vrged <hi>Canaanitiſh vncircumciſion</hi> and <hi>ſpirituall fornication,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 2. Mat. 15.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they ſeduced the people of God from their pure and <hi>chaſt</hi> Religion and <hi>ſeruice</hi> of him,<note place="margin">Iſa. 57.</note> through their <hi>Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous traditions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>fourth</hi> is, the <hi>crime</hi> theſe lay to the charge of this <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:12429:15"/>
chaſt wife <hi>[The Church]</hi> which is <hi>Adultery,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A young man come to her and lay with her. <hi>Ezek. 16. 1. Cor. 5. Iac. 4.</hi>
                     </note> that is to ſay, a <hi>violation</hi> of the Law of God in point of <hi>Relligion,</hi> which by the <hi>mouth</hi> of God is called <hi>Spiritual Adultery:</hi> and a <hi>violation</hi> of the Law of <hi>man</hi> in point of <hi>ſociety,</hi> which is alſo by the Spirit of God termed, the <hi>Adultery of the world.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> The <hi>fifth</hi> is, the <hi>vindication</hi> of the <hi>Innocency</hi> of this chaſt <hi>ſpouſe</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> of God. And that, out of the mouth of the <hi>Accuſers</hi> themſelues, in their <hi>examinations (ſeuerally</hi> taken) found contrary one to the other</p>
                  <p>(<hi>Obſerue here the weakneſſes of iudgement giuen, vpon</hi> Teſtimonies joyntly taken <hi>before men, how circumſpect ſoeuer otherwiſe; and how eaſily the</hi> moſt ſufficient vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings <hi>may bee ſeduced and abuſed therein. To which onely end, this circumſtance ſeemeth to be inſerted.</hi>)</p>
                  <p>And herein are we to conſider the matter of their <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions,</hi> whereby the falſhood of their <hi>Teſtimonies</hi> is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, namely, that the one nameth the place to be vnder a <hi>Lentiſque</hi> Tree; the other, vnder a <hi>Scarlat-bery Holme</hi> Tree. Wherein <hi>literally</hi> is ſhewed (out of the difference of theſe two Trees;) the impoſſibilitie that either that thing ſhould bee trew, which theſe falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes did arme with ſuch <hi>contrary circumſtances;</hi> Or that they ſhould be miſtaken in the <hi>ſenſible</hi> differences of ſuch manifeſt <hi>obiects.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For firſt, both theſe Trees are obſerued to haue on them through the whole yeare, both leaues and fruite; ſo that there could not bee wanting vnto theſe <hi>Accuſers</hi> ſufficient appearance of their <hi>differences.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of the <hi>Lentiſque</hi> is thus ſung.</p>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Iam verò ſemper viridis, ſemperque grauata.</l>
                        <l>Lentiſcus triplici ſolita eſt grandeſcere foetu</l>
                        <l>Ter fruges fundens.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <note place="margin">Plin.</note>
                           <hi>The</hi> Lentiſque <hi>euer greene, thrice yeerely burgeoneth,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Thrice yeerely rendereth fruite and flouriſheth.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:12429:15"/>And of this kinde of <hi>Holme</hi> is recorded.<note place="margin">Plin.</note>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Ilici folia non decidunt —</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Scarlat</hi> Holme <hi>ſheddeth not leaues.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And againe:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ilex annifera, novuſque fructus illis cum annotino pendet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Scarlet Holme</hi> beareth fruite the whole yeare, and ſhee hath new ſprung fruite on her together with the fruite of the former yeare.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, both theſe Trees are acknowlaged to bee <hi>Arbores indigenae:</hi> Trees naturally growing and breeding in that countrey, and of much and <hi>often vſe</hi> among the People there, So that the <hi>youngeſt</hi> child that can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne of things among them according to <hi>Naturall ſenſe,</hi> cannot bee ignorant of the <hi>Difference</hi> of theſe two Trees.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Differences</hi> of them, either from other are found theſe.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Lentiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </hi> hath the leaues of a deepe greene colour, &amp; the edges of the leaues, and the ribbes or veines ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what red. But this ſort of <hi>Holme</hi> hath leaues greene on the vpper ſide (but not ſo darke) and white vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath.</p>
                  <p>The leaues of the <hi>Lentiſque</hi> doe reſemble them of the <hi>Licorice,</hi> or <hi>Oliue.</hi> But the leaues of this kinde of <hi>Holme</hi> are like them of the <hi>Bay</hi> and prickly in manner of a Saw.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Lentiſque</hi> fruite is firſt moſſy flowers in <hi>cluſters</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on long ſtems, after which comen beries like <hi>Fitches</hi> or <hi>Elder-beryes,</hi> firſt greene, then purple, and laſt of all blacke, which fruite is ſometimes preſſed into an Oyle; and ſometimes is ſeaſoned into a <hi>Sallade.</hi> But this ſort of <hi>Holme</hi> hath firſt an <hi>Acorne</hi> like the <hi>Oake,</hi> though ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſmaller, yet ſuch as many vſe for <hi>bread</hi> in time of penury of Grayne; And afterward hath a Bery cleau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the boughes, without ſtemme (other then as the <hi>Oake</hi>-apple) and of the bigneſſe of a Peaſe, or lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle other; coloured firſt White, after Aſhcolour; in which is gendred the vermine, whereof is made the rich
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12429:16"/>
                     <hi>Scarlat</hi> dye <hi>[Coccus Baphicus]</hi> by vs called <hi>Coccianel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The barque of the <hi>Lentiſque</hi> is bright red, and is (as are the barques of thoſe <hi>teary</hi> Trees) thin,<note place="margin">The gummes of all theſe ſorts of trees are properly called <hi>Lacrymae,</hi> Teares.</note> and apt to bee wounded, and to ſend forth their <hi>teares,</hi> thoſe precious <hi>Gummes</hi> they yeeld.</p>
                  <p>But the barque of this ſort of <hi>Holme</hi> is very darke red inclining to blackneſſe, and is thicke and dry and ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy like that of the <hi>Corke</hi>-Tree, inſomuch as in ſome places the one is vſed inſteed of the other.</p>
                  <p>Theſe obſeruations as they are deliuered by the moſt approued Authors, <hi>Dioſcorides, Galen, Cic. Plin. Matthiolus, Amatus Luſitanus, Dodoneus, Geſner, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard,</hi> &amp;c. may ſuffice to ſhew, that it ought not to bee reckoned vnlikely or hard for a childe, to cloſe theſe two falſe <hi>Accuſers</hi> in the net they had laide for the <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent;</hi> And euen ſo eaſie was it for any that were not hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in miſchiefe, to diſcouer the accuſations laide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Primitiue Church</hi> by the <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> to bee ſo <hi>incompatible</hi> in one and the ſame <hi>ſubiect,</hi> as it muſt of neceſſity appeare to haue proceeded not out of <hi>Trewth,</hi> but of meere enuy and malice, that they were ſo charged with them.</p>
                  <p>What out of the Nature of theſe two Trees ſeuerally conſidered doth farther ariſe, is properly pertaining to the <hi>Accompliſhment</hi> following.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The Accompliſhment.</head>
                  <p>THe <hi>Primitiue Church</hi> at the firſt, (that is to ſay, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> diſperſed themſelues from <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> into all parts of the world) conſiſted onely of <hi>priuate</hi> perſons, and was as a wife in the houſe, without any commanding power in order as to the <hi>Publique ſtate.</hi> And had theſe two Aduerſaries, the <hi>Heathen Idolatry,</hi>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:12429:16"/>
and the <hi>Ieweſh ſuperſtition,</hi> euermore ſtanding forth in accuſation againſt it. By which it ſuffered grieuous <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions</hi> and <hi>Martyrdomes,</hi> through their <hi>Calumnies</hi> put into the eares of the Emperours, and Kings of the earth yet <hi>Infidels</hi> and <hi>vnconuerted.</hi> Which as I haue ſaide did no better agree together, then that two Trees ſo much different, ſhould be ſaide to reſemble one the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or to be of one and the ſame kinde.</p>
                  <p>But what if wee ſhall ſay, that out of the <hi>Appellatiue</hi> names of theſe two Trees, are foretold what kinde of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations ſhould be brought againſt it by either of them? Certainly when I conſider the Nature of them both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, with the reference they haue to the perſons to whoſe <hi>Accuſations</hi> they are adpropriate, I cannot but vnderſtand ſome ſpeciall <hi>Myſterie</hi> hidden in it.</p>
                  <p>For firſt to the <hi>Gentile</hi> is allotted the <hi>Lentiſque</hi> Tree, whoſe teare is that vſuall gumme <hi>Maſtique,</hi> ſo ſeruicea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto them that ſtudy wholy for the outward beauty and graciouſneſſe of the body, as if (with the <hi>Epicure</hi>) they made the pleaſure and contentment thereof their <hi>Summum bonum</hi> and onely end. And ſo did the <hi>Gentiles</hi> lay to the charge of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that vnder pretence of their religious meetings, they gaue themſelues whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>Anarchy, Senſuality,</hi> and <hi>carnall liberty,</hi> which muſt breed a <hi>reiection</hi> of all good <hi>Gouernment, Order, and care</hi> of the common good. And on the other ſide, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as to the <hi>Iew,</hi> is adſcribed this kinde of <hi>Holme</hi>-Tree, whoſe beryes (as I ſhewed before) yeeld that precious dye (which pertaines onely to the <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>great ſtates-men</hi> of the world to bee attired in). So the accuſations which theſe men brought againſt the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> were (altogether or for the moſt part) matters of <hi>Ambition, Treaſon,</hi> and <hi>Innouation,</hi> as if they aſpired to a worldly Power and Souerainty. And this they charged them with, thereby to make them odious to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> in whoſe hand the <hi>ſtate</hi> then was. And if either of theſe hapned to change into the others <hi>Arguments,</hi> it procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12429:17"/>
of the lyding they bare either towards other againſt theſe <hi>Chriſtians</hi> whom they had ſet vp for the <hi>Common enemie</hi> to them both; and not of their owne <hi>Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But <hi>Daniel [the iudgement of God]</hi> ſteping forth in the mouth of ſundry learned men,<note place="margin">Iuſtinus. Ariſtides. Athenagoras. Tertullian. Vid. Euſeb.</note> (which were not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding but <hi>Priuate,</hi> and as it were vnder age in order as to the <hi>State</hi>) by their <hi>Diſcrete</hi> and juſt <hi>Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies</hi> doe make manifeſt, both to <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> the <hi>Innocency,</hi> and holineſſe of <hi>conuerſation</hi> among the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> and ſo their cauſe being heard they are acquieted, and thoſe falſe Iudges, (the <hi>Heathen,</hi> and the <hi>Iewiſh Lawes) exautorate</hi> as <hi>condemned to death,</hi> and the <hi>Trewth</hi> of God in the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> generally approued, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
                  <p>The laſt <hi>Circumſtance</hi> is, of the great <hi>reputation</hi> that (vpon his judgement giuen) the young Prophet grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto among the people. For after that the <hi>Integrity</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> was made thoroughly knowne;<note place="margin">Sella in Curali ſtruma Nonius ſedet, Per con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulatum peierat Vatinius. Catul.</note> they increaſed dayly in number and power; the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> obtaining the more credit, by meanes that men did looke into the intolerable miſchiefes and furies of the impious, when they were in <hi>Authority,</hi> and the fearefull plagues and puniſhments ſent by God among them, which were <hi>Defenders</hi> of <hi>Idolatrie</hi> and <hi>Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſo this <hi>Period</hi> is continued, from the <hi>Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the <hi>Moſaical Church</hi> (where the former <hi>Period</hi> ended,) for ſo long time as the <hi>Primitiue Church Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> is in <hi>Priuate</hi> eſtate, and not receiued into place of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraine Gouernment;</hi> as is repreſented both by the <hi>Sex</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> of a wife, and the <hi>childhood</hi> of the <hi>Prophet.</hi> Namely, the times of the <hi>Church</hi> as they are by Saint <hi>John typed</hi> vnder the <hi>Epheſine, Smyrnaean,</hi> and <hi>Pergamine Churches;</hi> The viſions of the opening of the <hi>Seales;</hi> of the <hi>Queene of Heauen in trauel;</hi> and the <hi>King of Heauen and earth borne,</hi> which was vntil by <hi>Publique</hi> Edict, the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12429:17"/>
Crowne was ſet vpon the <hi>Head of Chriſt,</hi> and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes were acknowlaged the Lords, and the bynding power to pertaine alonely to <hi>Chriſt</hi> and to his Lawes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third Period is of an Jdola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Culture.</head>
               <p>AN entrance is made into this <hi>Paſſage</hi> by a <hi>ſolemne Preface</hi> (for preparation) taken from the time, when, it is to be obſerued to haue beginning. Namely after the <hi>change</hi> of the <hi>Imperial ſtate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now in this <hi>Preamble,</hi> firſt is to be noted,<note place="margin">When King Aſly ages was laide with his Fathers Cyrus the Perſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> receiued his Kingdome.</note> that <hi>Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally</hi> it ſeemeth a manifeſt abſurdity, vnworthy the <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of <hi>Prophecie,</hi> to make mention of <hi>Aſtyages,</hi> as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Babilon.</hi> For albeit, that trew it is, that <hi>Cyrus</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Aſtyages</hi> in his Kingdome, yet this taken, as I ſay, according to the letter, is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impertinent to the matters of <hi>Babilon.</hi> For <hi>Aſtyages</hi> was King of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> and not of <hi>Babilon;</hi> And the ſucceſſion of <hi>Cyrus</hi> vnto him, was in his owne right of inheritance to the Crowne of <hi>Media</hi> and <hi>Perſia,</hi> for hee was the ſonne of <hi>Cambyſes</hi> a <hi>Perſian,</hi> and <hi>Maudane</hi> the onely daughter of the ſaide <hi>Aſtyages,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Thereof was <hi>Cyrus</hi> (by the Oracle) called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. A Mule, becauſ he had a <hi>Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> to Father, &amp; a <hi>Mede</hi> to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Gen. 10. Gen. 7.</note> who was a <hi>Mede</hi> by birth: ſo that hee could by no meanes make title to the Crowne of <hi>Babilon,</hi> not from the very firſt <hi>diſperſion</hi> of peoples vnto their ſeuerall ſeates. For <hi>Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> came of <hi>Cham;</hi> But the <hi>Medes</hi> from <hi>Iaphet,</hi> and the <hi>Perſians</hi> from <hi>Shem,</hi> and from theſe two later (as is ſhewed) came <hi>Cyrus.</hi> So that in this <hi>tranſlation</hi> of the Empire of <hi>Babilon</hi> to the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> is no rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to humane <hi>right,</hi> that <hi>Aſtyages</hi> ſhould bee mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; But in it, is (firſt) accompliſhed the <hi>bleſſing</hi> of <hi>Noah</hi> vpon his two elder ſonnes, and his <hi>curſe</hi> vpon the younger; And (ſecondly,) the <hi>burden</hi> vpon <hi>Babilon</hi> from
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12429:18"/>
God in the mouth of his <hi>Prophets,</hi> perſonally calling forth <hi>Cyrus</hi> to the performance of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 44. &amp; 45.</note>In the ſecond place therefore, the <hi>ſpiritual ſenſe</hi> of this <hi>Introduction</hi> yeeldeth more <hi>Grace.</hi> For the name <hi>Aſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages</hi> duely ſearched into, ſignifieth <hi>One,</hi> that not ſo by <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>right</hi> as by <hi>crafty Policy,</hi> and <hi>violent Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> hath the rule of the People;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aſtyages.</hi> Tyrannus.</note> And ſuch were thoſe, that had the <hi>Empire</hi> of the world, and of the Kingdomes of the <hi>Heathen,</hi> in the time of their ignorance concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Chriſt;</hi> vntil it pleaſed God to ſend and ſet ouer them <hi>Cyrus,</hi> the <hi>Subſtitute of his Heire</hi> (as the name bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth),<note place="margin">Cyrus. <hi>Pro-haeres. Pſa. 2.</hi> And Daniel did eate at the Kings table, and was honored aboue al his friends.</note> namely <hi>Chriſtian Princes,</hi> the Lieutenants of <hi>Christ Ieſus,</hi> the <hi>Heire Apparant,</hi> and <hi>Lord Paraumont</hi> of Heauen and Earth; which as they acknowlage to Reigne by <hi>God;</hi> ſo they conforme the whole <hi>Reaſon</hi> of their Gouernment to the Plat-forme of <hi>his Law.</hi> Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that wherein ſo euer their Lawes are not <hi>Regulated</hi> by it; their Rules are <hi>Tyrannicall and inordinate,</hi> how faire a ſhew ſoeuer they make otherwiſe. And in this ſort is <hi>Daniel</hi> taken into preſence and conuerſation with the King and State in <hi>Babilon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus then (by this Preface) we are prepared to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, when this <hi>Idolatrous Culture</hi> is timed to be in <hi>Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</hi> Namely, after the change of the Empire thereof, from vnder the Curſe, to pertaine to the Promiſe; that is to ſay, from <hi>Heatheniſh Idolatry</hi> to the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of the <hi>liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God in Christ;</hi> and yet the ſeate of the Empire conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth ſtill in <hi>Babilon;</hi> which becauſe it was not found in the old <hi>Babilon:</hi> for it was vtterly ruined and deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſo continueth euen to this day (in order, as to Impery, as appeareth by that which hath beene ſaide before). Therefore it muſt of neceſſity bee verified in the <hi>NEW;</hi> and this <hi>Idolatry,</hi> ſpoken of it (not as it was before <hi>[Ethnique]</hi> But) as it is now become <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> and had ſworne <hi>Homage</hi> and <hi>fealty</hi> to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> the <hi>Chriſtian Cyrus</hi> of the <hi>Empire,</hi> and in <hi>Lucius</hi> our <hi>Chriſtian Cyrus</hi> of this Land of <hi>Albion,</hi> and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12429:18"/>
ſo of other Kingdomes reſpectiuely. And thereupon commeth into queſtion the <hi>Idolatrous Culture</hi> of the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilonian,</hi> whereof this third <hi>Period</hi> hath to ſpeake of.</p>
               <p>In which, the firſt thing to be conſidered is,<note place="margin">The Babilonians had at Idol cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Bel.</note> of the <hi>Jdol Belus</hi> or <hi>Bel.</hi> The <hi>Appellatiue</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] if it be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken after the <hi>Original</hi> vſe, for <hi>[Rei verae effigies],</hi> the ſhape of a trew thing. <hi>(For ſo it is ſaide, that the Lacedemonians did carry about</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] <hi>the Idol of their dead King in a bed well adorned or ſet forth),</hi> And the name <hi>Belus</hi> for the proper name of the firſt <hi>founder</hi> of that <hi>Empire;</hi> then doth it in <hi>Prophetical Language</hi> import, that this <hi>ſecond Babilon</hi> ſhould (notwithſtanding their profeſſed <hi>conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> to <hi>Gods</hi> Lawes, and to <hi>Chriſtianity</hi>) ſtill hold in <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration,</hi> and euen to <hi>Idolatry, adore</hi> the <hi>Heathen</hi> Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of their <hi>founder,</hi> (as <hi>Belus</hi> was to the old <hi>Babilon</hi>) and his <hi>Succeſſors,</hi> in their <hi>National Diſcipline.</hi> Which how trewly wee finde euen to this day verified among them, is ſo manifeſt; as I ſuppoſe it would ſeeme ſuperflous to men of knowlage and vnderſtanding, to haue report made vnto them of it, whether in their Lawes <hi>Ciuil, Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conomical,</hi> or <hi>Moral.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>(For this point and ſome others, I haue choſen to referre the Reader to the obſeruation of particulars, as they are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious in many that haue formerly written to thoſe purpoſes, and paſſe by the inſtances of them my ſelfe, leaſt I might both bee thought to haue drawne the waters of other mens Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines into mine owne Cisterns; and alſo that the labour ſelfe might not grow to a greater bulke, then that might bee no way greiuous to the meaneſt to purchaſe it.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And theſe lawes (though not according to their <hi>Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tables,</hi> yet to the <hi>Acception</hi> of their <hi>Brutiſh</hi> ſpirits) ſo inuiolable, as were the Lawes of that <hi>Dracons,</hi> of whom it is ſaide, hee wrote them not in Inke, but in <hi>Bloud.</hi> Witneſſe the <hi>ſeuerity</hi> of them, vpon their owne children, yea, vpon their owne ſelues, in caſe of breach of their Lawes, though perforcely committed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:12429:19"/>But if the <hi>Appellatiue</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] bee taken as by a <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundary Intention,</hi> for the Repreſentation of a feigned thing;<note place="margin">And the King worſhipped it, &amp; went dayly to honor it.</note> And this <hi>Name [Belus]</hi> be drawne from that common Name of <hi>Bahal</hi> after the <hi>Radical Hebrew,</hi> or <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> the <hi>Chaldaean</hi> ſprout thereof, and vſed for any Lord hauing and exerciſing <hi>Diuine</hi> Power and Right of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety</hi> ouer <hi>Perſons</hi> or <hi>things;</hi> Then doth it diſcouer vnto vs, in what ſteede theſe <hi>New-Babilonians</hi> ſhould hold the faith of <hi>God in Chriſt.</hi> Namely, with ſuch <hi>Reference</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Imaginary Patrons</hi> and <hi>Coadiutors</hi> (if not chiefe <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors</hi>) of their vowes and prayers in <hi>ſpecial</hi> to bee obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, as ſhould bee beſt for the promotion of the cauſe of their <hi>Politique reſpect</hi> in <hi>general.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now what is the multitude of their <hi>Canonized Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors</hi> (howſoeuer in ſhew they ſerue to ſet Forth their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary <hi>Deuotion</hi> and <hi>Humility,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coloſ. 2.</note> as to the <hi>Particular</hi>) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then (for the trewth of it in <hi>General,</hi>) like to their owne Countrey <hi>North-Eaſt</hi> winde, the more lofty, the more cloudy?<note place="margin">Ater thit expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens mendaci nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bila ſtatu— Cae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ias.</note> So doe they as juglers lift vp their eyes moſt fixedly to Heauen, thereby to draw the <hi>ſpectators</hi> eyes to accompanie theirs, when they the meane while may the more vnperceiuedly bring to paſſe their <hi>Legier-du-maine,</hi> and earthly ends. Namely, to get credit where they moſt purpoſe to deceiue, and to purchaſe opinion of loue and frendſhip, where they ſeeke ſooneſt and moſt <hi>ſummary deſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that this is to be vnderſtood of them, The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thing to bee conſidered,<note place="margin">In that ſame place was a great Dragon, which the Babilonians worſhipped.</note> (Namely, the <hi>trew</hi> and liuely preſence of this their <hi>Imaginary Belus</hi>) doth make to appeare, which is (indeede) found to bee a <hi>Dragon.</hi> And euen ſo is their <hi>Relligion</hi> made in ſhew to bee <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, Reaſonable, Gratious, Godly,</hi> as by the <hi>Idol.</hi> But is in trewth <hi>Beſtial, Cruel, Bloudy, Deuilliſh,</hi> as by the <hi>Dragon,</hi> whereof let none others but their owne Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords be brought forth to witneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As in Diuine letters, the Character of the Diuel is a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12429:19"/>
Dragon; and Idolatry called Deuils worſhip.</hi> 1. Cor. 10. <hi>So in Pagan-learning the</hi> Hieroglyphique <hi>of Witch-craft (which is the Inuocation of Deuils) is a</hi> Dragon, (<hi>as by the Poet</hi>-Nunc ego Medeae vellem fraenare Dracones-) <hi>To intimate, that the Man that doth either ſet vp, or ſo much as conniue at</hi> Idolatry, <hi>doth thereby make himſelfe fit, both to worke, and to bee wrought vpon, by</hi> Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft. <hi>Whereof what plentiful</hi> Inſtances <hi>wee haue had in the</hi> New-Babilonian Idolatry, <hi>I ſuppoſe none but the deafe</hi> Neighborers <hi>of</hi> Nilus ouerfalls <hi>are ignorant of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, if there bee any that will needes haue this Idol of <hi>Belus,</hi> to expreſſe the whole of their <hi>Relligion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">There were ſpent vpon this Idol e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day twelue great meaſures, &amp;c.</note> to ſtand in the worſhip of thoſe trunkiſh Gods they call vpon, and the <hi>Realty</hi> of this their worſhip to bee the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the <hi>old Dragon</hi> the <hi>Deuil;</hi> Or thirdly, if any will otherwiſe haue the Idol <hi>Belus</hi> to bee that <hi>Great Mounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bancque</hi> their <hi>Pope;</hi> and the <hi>Dragon</hi> that <hi>Infernal Conclaue of Cardinals,</hi> whoſe onely breath doth enliue that <hi>Idol;</hi> Or if there bee any other <hi>light</hi> here in emparted to others of my brethren in the <hi>Miniſtery</hi> of the <hi>Prophecie</hi> of our <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> I will not refuſe to joyne with them, ſo farre forth as they make the parts to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree and moue together, as in this they are found to doe.</p>
               <p>As wee haue hitherto beene enformed touching the <hi>forme</hi> of this <hi>Idolatry:</hi> ſo in the third place wee are taught, what to eſteeme of it in reſpect of the <hi>end,</hi> and that is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in phraſes of ſpeech pertaining to foode, where is to be obſerued, that to the <hi>dead Idol</hi> is offered an vnmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable dayly allowance of meate and drinke; whereas it could not be vnknowne to any <hi>Reaſonable creature,</hi> that the <hi>Idol</hi> could take none. And on the other ſide, the <hi>Dragon</hi> was acknowlaged to liue by foode, and there is none found to bee offered vnto him. And ſuch are the ends of this their double dealing <hi>Impiety,</hi> according to the ſaying.</p>
               <q>Simulata ſanctitas duplicata iniquitas.</q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:12429:20"/>For the former their <hi>Belus</hi> or <hi>Belly-god,</hi> doth ſet forth their inſatiable <hi>Couetize,</hi> according to the word of their chiefe <hi>Miniſter:</hi>
                  <q>Non ſufficit Orbis.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And the later their <hi>Dragonly policy</hi> ſheweth their <hi>vnli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited Ambition,</hi> whereby they haue in conceipt already ſwallowed vp Heauen and Hell, and yet are not ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>But God be thanked, it is not found in our <hi>Prophecy,</hi> that either of them taketh any ſuſtenance. For <hi>[Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon is fallen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ap. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>it is fallen,]</hi> and that by <hi>Daniel,</hi> firſt diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering vnto <hi>Chriſtian Princes and Magiſtrates,</hi> the ſly conueighances of theſe <hi>Babilonian Impoſtures.</hi> And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, remouing the <hi>preiudicate</hi> conceipt of their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable force and ſtrength.</p>
               <p>The former, (Namely, the diſcouery of their <hi>Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>) is by tracting their footſteps in <hi>aſhes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Daniele comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his ſeruants to bring aſhes, and theſe they ſtrawed, &amp;c.</note> And <hi>aſhes</hi> is that which is left of the <hi>diſſolued</hi> bodies of the <hi>dead,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Animals</hi> or <hi>Vegetables.</hi> So did the diſcreete wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Relligious Princes,</hi> by the <hi>aduiſe</hi> of our <hi>Daniel (the iudgements of God)</hi> ſearch into the <hi>aſhes,</hi> that is to ſay, into the Records and Memorials left of the <hi>Deceſſors</hi> of theſe Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> and the fruites of their workes while they liued; And diſcouered whereto tended all their <hi>Hipocritical ſhew.</hi> Namely, to <hi>deuoure the whole earth,</hi> which how trew it is in them, let the <hi>dead</hi> ſpeake, as in all the world ouer,<note place="margin">Dan. 7.</note> ſo more ſpecially in theſe parts wherein wee liue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For</hi> France <hi>let the whole Treatiſe of</hi> La Cabinet du Roy de France, &amp;c. <hi>bee viewed; And for</hi> Germany, <hi>the Articles of the Diet at</hi> Wormes, Anno. 1521; <hi>and at</hi> Noriberg, Anno. 1523. <hi>be conſidered. And for</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>the ſundry paſſages of</hi> Fox <hi>in his Martyrology, and of</hi> Iewel <hi>in the defence of his</hi> Apology, <hi>and diuers others be called to accompt, as the footeſteps of thoſe times in</hi> aſhes, <hi>and it will appeare, that the greateſt part of the wealth and treaſures of theſe Lands (and conſequently of all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12429:20"/>
in Chriſtendeme) were in the hands of their</hi> Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaus, <hi>which (as horſeleaches when they are filled with bloud) this</hi> Belus <hi>and his</hi> Dragon <hi>did by ſalting and poudering them, make them to diſgorge into</hi> their <hi>cofers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The later, namely, the ouerweening of their irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtable power, is voided by the vſe of a <hi>Medicinal Pil</hi> miniſtred to them which, as it is not foode to giue nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment to their <hi>Nature,</hi> but <hi>Medicine</hi> to worke vpon and alter <hi>Nature.</hi> So there is no hope by faire meanes to preuaile with them (for <hi>Improbitas nullo flectitur obſequio</hi>) but the <hi>Humors</hi> abounding in them muſt bee met with and <hi>ſubdued.</hi> As appeareth by the <hi>Ingredients.</hi> Firſt;<note place="margin">Daniel tooke fat, and pitch, and haire, and boyled them together, and made lumps thereof. This did he put into the Dragons mouth, &amp; ſo the Drago<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> burst in ſunder.</note> all of them are things <hi>not</hi> ſuffering <hi>Putrefaction</hi> eaſily.</p>
               <p>Next they are euery one in their kinde, apt to joyne with the other of them; ſo that while their <hi>Natures</hi> in themſelues remaine <hi>vndeſtroyed,</hi> it is very <hi>hard to ſeuer</hi> them one from the other.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, they haue a <hi>glutinous</hi> and clammy quality, wherby they are hardly remoued from the place or thing, whereto they are once made to <hi>cleaue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that by the <hi>Ingredients</hi> of theſe <hi>Pils</hi> are three princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal vertues commended to vs, by which this <hi>venimous Beaſt</hi> is to bee deſtroyed. For</p>
               <p>Their <hi>Incorruptibleneſſe</hi> of themſelues, doth betoken <hi>vnity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Inſeperableneſſe</hi> either from other, doth deſigne <hi>ſecrecy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Vnremoueableneſſe</hi> from whereto they are apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is <hi>Conſtancy</hi> and <hi>Perſeuerance,</hi> which the <hi>Daniels</hi> of <hi>Nations</hi> in their <hi>Councils</hi> are to vſe for performance of this <hi>Rare Cure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thoſe that wil in a more literal manner haue it vnderſtood, that theſe Materials, being of ſpecial vſe in Sea ſeruices</hi> (as the Tallow for ſpeedy way,<note place="margin">—Natat vncta carina.</note> the Pitch for ſtanch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the Haire for defence againſt Orcs and gnawing Wormes,) <hi>doe intimate the manner how this</hi> Dragon <hi>is to bee taken out of the way. Namely, by a</hi> Nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12429:21"/>
expedition <hi>againſt the</hi> Den <hi>of his abode; theſe doe herein commend vnto vs the vertues of Integrity, Secricy, and Expedition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo vpon the Mater both theſe come to one, in Point of Performance.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The Accompliſhment.</head>
                  <p>THis third <hi>Period</hi> wee finde to haue beene taken vp with the <hi>diſcouery</hi> of the viperous <hi>generation</hi> of <hi>Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, Schiſmes,</hi> and <hi>Heatheniſh impieties,</hi> in Maters as well of <hi>Church</hi> as of <hi>Comon-wealth,</hi> put vpon the <hi>Church,</hi> vnder the maſque of <hi>Relligion.</hi> All which haue bin either firſt bred and begun, or otherwiſe by Protection and Maintenance,<note place="margin">See for this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion Image of both Churches Acts &amp; Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Iniquity. <hi>Piſgah Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica.</hi> Problemes concerning Antichriſt: and a million moe, both Ancient and Moderne. Ap. 2. &amp; 3.</note> ſeconded and continued by the <hi>New Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon.</hi> And haue beene brought to their Tryal by <hi>[Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel] The iudgements of God,</hi> in the mouth of <hi>faithful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,</hi> and in the hand of <hi>zelous Magiſtrates.</hi> As wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thoſe Armies of <hi>Holy Profeſſors</hi> from time to time; and their vnweried ſpirits, in the encounters and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats they maintained euen to death, againſt this <hi>Babilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Belus</hi> and <hi>his Dragon,</hi> and their <hi>Sectaries</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their <hi>Tenents,</hi> ſo farre forth as they were not <hi>Regular,</hi> and <hi>Demonſtrable</hi> out of the <hi>Arche-type</hi> of <hi>Gods word</hi> and <hi>Law.</hi> By meanes whereof, the <hi>New Babilon</hi> is brought into <hi>contempt</hi> with all <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>People</hi> of vnderſtanding; And <hi>Belus</hi> and his houſe and his Prieſts deſtroyed, by abrogating the bynding power of his lawes; And his <hi>Dragon</hi> ſlaine, by remouing the <hi>Pagan policy,</hi> and by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhing the place of their <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> prouocations. And ſo doth conclude with the <hi>deſtruction</hi> of <hi>Babilon the later,</hi> which is (at the length) to be as <hi>Real</hi> as was that of the former.</p>
                  <p>Thus this <hi>Period</hi> of our <hi>Prophet</hi> doth ſquare with thoſe <hi>Reuelations</hi> of the <hi>Euangelical Diuine,</hi> deliuered vnder the <hi>types</hi> of the <hi>Thyatirian</hi> and <hi>Sardeian Churches,</hi> and the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12429:21"/>
viſions of <hi>Michael</hi> and his <hi>Angels,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ap. 12. 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c.</note> and of the <hi>Dragon</hi> and his <hi>Beaſts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The forth <hi>Period</hi> is of a <hi>tumultuous Conſpiracie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS to a turbulent enterpriſe among the multitude, it is not found, that they vſe any precedent <hi>conſideration,</hi> either touching <hi>Motiues, Manner</hi> of doing, or <hi>Ends,</hi> but
<q>Quâ data porta ruunt —</q>
               </p>
               <p>They are cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed headlong, they neither know nor care whither:<note place="margin">When the Babilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians heard it, they were won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous wroth &amp; gathered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues together againſt the King</note> So needed not any Preface by way of <hi>connexion</hi> to bee inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, betwixt the former <hi>Period</hi> of thoſe <hi>Babilonians</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed <hi>wrongs,</hi> by demoliſhing their <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and this of their vnquenchable thirſt of <hi>Reuenge;</hi> but that the <hi>Hint</hi> of that, ſhould (according to their <hi>Brutiſh Natures</hi>) ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily draw on their outragiouſneſſe in this, to their owne confuſion.</p>
               <p>In which we haue firſt to conſider, that by theſe <hi>Tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Babilonians</hi> are deſigned, what <hi>inordinate Conſpiracies</hi> the <hi>Sectaries</hi> of the <hi>Myſtical Babilon</hi> would enterpriſe, now that they are made headleſſe, by the <hi>conuiction</hi> of the dead truncke of their <hi>Idol Bel-Pope,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Saying deliuer vs Daniel, or elſe we will deſtroy thee and thy houſe.</note> and the <hi>Ignis fatuus</hi> of their <hi>Cardinal Dragons Conclaue.</hi> All which their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendments</hi> and <hi>Conſpiracyes</hi> are againſt the <hi>Church,</hi> vpon pretence of maintaining their old <hi>(Antichriſtian) Rel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> and <hi>Policy,</hi> which the trew <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth indeede mainely oppoſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">In the Den were ſeuen Lyons.</note> the ſeuen Lyons are an <hi>Heptarchy</hi> of an <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous</hi> people which ſhall bee by theſe <hi>Antichriſtian Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilonians</hi> in all places ſtirred vp,<note place="margin">Ier. 51, 17.</note> as <hi>brute Beaſts exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> by famine, to the ſpoile and deuouring of the <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:12429:22"/>
                  <note place="margin">They caſt him into the Lyons Den.</note>Thirdly, the ſixe daies or weekes-worke of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> impriſonment is, a terme of time in which <hi>Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors</hi> of trew <hi>Relligion</hi> ſhall (notwithſtanding) be giuen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to be drawne into <hi>brutiſh and prophane courſes and waies,</hi> and to the compaſſing of <hi>earthly</hi> ends, as worldly mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men doe in the weeke dayes, to the labors and cares of fleſh and bloud; without any <hi>reference</hi> of their workes, to the ſetting forth of <hi>Gods glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vpon the ſeuenth day the King went to bewayle Daniel.</note>But on the ſeuenth, that is the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo ſoone as they ſettle to a ſerious <hi>reformation</hi> of themſelues in the <hi>ſeruice</hi> of God according to his will and <hi>ordinance;</hi> they ſhall bee releaſed and rewarded (for that they haue ſuffered) with <hi>double honor,</hi> according to the <hi>rites</hi> of the <hi>Sabbatical Culture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, the ſhutting of the <hi>Lyons</hi> mouths is, the louing care of the <hi>Almighty</hi> ouer them that feare him and truſt in him,<note place="margin">When he came nigh the Den hee looked in, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Daniel ſat in the midst of the Lyons <hi>Num. 24.</hi>
                  </note> whereby notwithſtanding their many <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors</hi> and <hi>wrenches</hi> betwixt God and them; yet are they (by his holy hand holden ouer them) ſafe amidſt thoſe <hi>furious</hi> people, and that in recompence (whereunto theſe people are guided by God, as <hi>Balaam</hi> was to bleſſe the <hi>Iſraelites</hi>) for the <hi>inuitation</hi> they had by them, to the acknowlagement of Gods glory and power in the <hi>firſt Period.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">There was in Iewry a Prophet, called <hi>Habaq.</hi>
                  </note>Fifthly, the foode miraculouſly brought by the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,</hi> may bee taken for the <hi>Succors</hi> that by Gods <hi>Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> ſhall come <hi>vnexpectedly</hi> to the <hi>faithful</hi> from farre, and very ſwifty and ſtrongly. Or elſe it may bee according to a <hi>moral</hi> vnderſtanding, taken for an <hi>admonition</hi> to the <hi>faithful,</hi> that they make recourſe to the <hi>gracious</hi> medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions deliuered by that <hi>Prophet</hi> (literally to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> but <hi>Myſtically</hi> pertaining to all faithfull <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in that caſe), as vnto the ſpiritual foode of their ſoules, the word of God therein. Namely, that albeit God doth chaſtiſe his Children by the <hi>rod</hi> of the wicked, as here in the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Daniel:</hi> yet they ſhould not therefore <hi>fall from their hope,</hi> as here hee may bee ſaide to ſpeake vnto <hi>Daniel;</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:12429:22"/>
But that <hi>[the godly and iuſt ſhall liue by their faith]</hi> and contraryly, the Impious, Oppreſſors,<note place="margin">Habaq. 2. 4.</note> Idolaters and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, ſhall periſh in their ſinnes. And this is the ſumme of that <hi>gracious Prophecie,</hi> which how fitly wee may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it to appertaine to this ſtate of the <hi>Church</hi> wherein <hi>Daniel</hi> is now made to bee; euery good <hi>Chriſtian</hi> may ſee.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, <hi>Daniel</hi> deliuered,<note place="margin">He drew him out of the Den and caſt them that were t e cauſe of his deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into the Den, and they were deuoured in a moment before his face.</note> and <hi>Lyons</hi> deuouring the <hi>Babilonians,</hi> is the turning of thoſe peoples hearts and forces againſt thoſe <hi>Babilonians</hi> that had ſtirred them vp to deſtroy the <hi>trew ſeruants of God,</hi> which when theſe <hi>faithfull</hi> ones ſhall behold, they ſhall tryumph and giue God the <hi>praiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seuenthly and laſtly, one thing is to be added which is not in the Text. For though it be not expreſſed, yet is it of neceſſity to bee vnderſtood; And that is how our <hi>Prophet</hi> ſpent all this time of his Bondage with the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? which out of <hi>Decency</hi> and <hi>Analogy</hi> with other Saints of God in like caſes as <hi>Manaſſes</hi> in the <hi>Dungeon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Chro. 33. Iona. 2. Dan. 3. 2. Cor. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Ionah</hi> in the <hi>Whailes</hi> belly, <hi>Paul</hi> in the depth of the <hi>Sea,</hi> and the <hi>Young men</hi> in the <hi>Fornace,</hi> (as in our firſt <hi>Period</hi>) muſt be vnderſtood, to haue beene <hi>firſt</hi> in <hi>Reconcilement</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> as touching former delicts (conſidered in this place, not altogether ſo much in reſpect of himſelfe, but <hi>ſpecially</hi> in the Perſon of his <hi>Nation;</hi> as hee doth alſo elſewhere). Secondly,<note place="margin">Dan. 9.</note> in <hi>thanksgiuing</hi> for his preſent preſeruation, and <hi>Petition</hi> of <hi>reliefe</hi> and comfort to bee continued; And thirdly, in <hi>Prophetical exultation</hi> vpon ſtedfaſt aſſurance, that hee ſhall be in good time deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and his Enemies taken in the Pit they haue made for others. And many meditations doe wee finde of this kinde, both in the booke of the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwhere,<note place="margin">Pſa. 3. &amp; 4.</note> diſperſed through the whole volume of the <hi>Holy Records.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:12429:23"/>
                  <head>The Accompliſhment.</head>
                  <p>VVHo ſo will enter into an <hi>accurate</hi> and diſcrete ſearch of the <hi>proceedings</hi> of theſe <hi>Babilonians,</hi> and compare their practiſes of theſe daies with thoe of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times; ſhal eaſily finde, how tenderly they take the late Entryes made vpon the <hi>freehold</hi> of their <hi>Conclaue,</hi> as well in word as in writing,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>King</hi> Iames <hi>in his Praemonito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Epiſtle, &amp;c. Novus homo.</hi>
                     </note> by ſundry worthy <hi>Agents</hi> in the cauſe of the <hi>Church.</hi> Specially a <hi>New man,</hi> which hath <hi>ex profeſſo,</hi> debated and proued out of their owne mouths euen by the Rules and Lawes of that their <hi>Conclaue,</hi> that there is not now, nor for long time paſt ſince, hath beene any <hi>Regularly</hi> made neither <hi>Pope</hi> nor <hi>Cardinal;</hi> wherefore from thence forth they haue not dealt (as they were wont before) by a ſhew of <hi>Legal</hi> proceedings, as by <hi>Excomunications, Interdicts, Jndulgences, Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>formalities.</hi> But now they plainly declare themſelues by <hi>Aſſaſinats, Leagues, Proſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Inuaſions, Breaches of promiſe and faith, Treaſons v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſal and particular,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Vid. Cancel. Hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pan.</note> as is diſcouered by their owne letters and <hi>Remonſtrances</hi> one to another, which they hoped ſhould neuer haue come to light in <hi>Teſtimony</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut. 29.17.</hi> O King bee not deceiued for this is but clay with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and braſſe without, and did neuer eate ought</note>And hereby they ſhew what reckoning they make and euer did, of their <hi>Dunguy Belas.</hi> Namely, no more then according to the matter whereof hee is made, <hi>[Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huſtan, a piece of braſſe, or a lumpe of clay].</hi> But the <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon</hi> in the <hi>Cage</hi> is that, which ſo long as they could beare the world in hand, of the life and ſtrength of it, they held themſelues ſafe enough. And now at length, they proclayme fire and ſword againſt <hi>Daniel</hi> and all the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> that call him to counſel againſt their <hi>Heath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eniſh Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Dragonly Policy,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The King is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>w, for he hath deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Bel, &amp;c.</note> and they are to them, <hi>Iewes,</hi> and worſe, that preſume to moue or to bee ſeene in it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:12429:23"/>Wherefore they haue ſtirred vp an <hi>Heptarchy</hi> of <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Claſſicum Belli ſacri.</note> that is to ſay, a full and <hi>competent</hi> power of ſundry Kingdomes (which as Lyons kept in dennes, are at their command) to ſet vpon <hi>Daniel</hi> and his followers, the ſincere Profeſſors of Gods trewth, who ſeeme to bee thereby vtterly forſaken by all their friends, and aſſailed on all ſides by <hi>Aduerſaries,</hi> in ſuch ineuitable diſtreſſe (as farre as man may diſcerne by the eye of fleſh and bloud) as if they were in a dungeon, among deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Beaſts. But they that behold them with <hi>ſpiritual</hi> eyes,<note place="margin">Period. 1.</note> doe contrarily ſee them as ſafe as they were before in the <hi>fornace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>Thoſe that out of much curioſity wil not be contented with the vnderſtanding of this Number of Seuen, after the for me of <hi>Prophetical</hi> ſpeech (wherein a Definite Number is vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally put for an Indefinite, as it is found in many places of the Canon of Holy writs, both Old and New) ſeeme to preſſe a <hi>Nominal</hi> deſignation of them. And ſo reckon <hi>France, Spaine,</hi> the <hi>Empire, Italy, Bohemia,</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> for ſixe of them. In ſome of which may bee perhaps ſome doubt. But for the ſeuenth, I cannot, neither doe I thinke any other will make doubt of. And that is, <hi>A home party</hi> in the boſome of the Church, and of all them of the trew Rel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which muſt needes bee the moſt dangerous, by how much the greatneſſe thereof is not poſſibly to bee diſcouered.</q>
                  <p>By this wee may perceiue, what is to be exſpected by the trew Profeſſors, from all thoſe that are at the <hi>Babilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> becke (<hi>ſpecially the laſt</hi> of the ſeuen named Lyons). <note place="margin">The home par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> Let them otherwiſe make what ſhew they will of <hi>ſociety</hi> and <hi>common Countrey,</hi> their bridle is the onely power of God, without any diſpoſition to peace in any of them. And it is a very dangerous <hi>Security</hi> in men, to ſet ſo light as they doe of that <hi>Tenent</hi> of theirs <hi>[How that it is a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal caſe of conſcience in them,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Fides non habe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Haereticis.</note> 
                     <hi>not to keepe faith with Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques.]</hi> For ſo conſequently it is to them a <hi>meritorious</hi> worke to purchaſe credit with the <hi>faithful,</hi> that ſo they may bee deceiued, and by their <hi>credulity</hi> vtterly cut off
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12429:24"/>
by theſe <hi>Infidels.</hi> Yea, and a ſinne <hi>inexpiable,</hi> for them to enter into any ſuch faith of league and ſociety with the trew Profeſſors, which they doe not before hand <hi>purpoſe</hi> and <hi>practiſe</hi> to breake when ſoeuer they ſhall ſee their beſt time to doe moſt miſchiefe thereby: ſo that it is leſſe perilous to truſt a <hi>Viper</hi> in the boſome, then theſe men vpon any termes. For that is felt at his firſt wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſo may the venime bee encountred and expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. But theſe are not felt to ſting, till the wound bee paſt recouery.</p>
                  <p>Howbeit for all this <hi>God</hi> hath not forſaken his people; but ſo ſoone as they turne and call to him, he will heare them,<note place="margin">Pſ. 46. <hi>Habaqquq.</hi> Affectionately embraceing.</note> and that right <hi>early;</hi> as hee doth our <hi>Prophet</hi> in the den, by the reliefe of <hi>Habaqquq,</hi> that is to ſay, ſuch as ſhall louingly embrace them in the acknowlagement of the trewth they profeſſe. Specially thoſe old <hi>Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors</hi> the <hi>Jewes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iehudah:</hi> Confeſſing or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rayſing.</note> who with <hi>new prayſes</hi> in their mouthes, that is to ſay, by their <hi>conuerſion</hi> vnto <hi>Chriſt</hi> their <hi>Meſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> ſhall either come themſelues with that <hi>irreſiſtible ſpeed,</hi> and vnperceiued <hi>ſecrecy,</hi> as if they were borne in the <hi>Aire,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>gelus.</hi> meſſenger or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſage.</note> by <hi>Angels,</hi> aboue the reach of mans ſight; Or elſe (as the <hi>name</hi> of <hi>Angel</hi> doth import) by meſſage of <hi>comfort</hi> from them, no leſſe ſpeedy then <hi>ſecret,</hi> of their <hi>mature aſſiſtance</hi> and <hi>confederacy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But when ſhall this bee (ſay ſome)? vnto whom it is anſwered, that it ſhall be ſo ſoone as we begin to <hi>hunger and thirſt</hi> after <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> as <hi>Daniel</hi> is to be vnderſtood to doe for <hi>natural foode,</hi> according to the long time of his ſtay in the Den.</p>
                  <p>Yea, and that by the <hi>ſpecial</hi> worke of <hi>God,</hi> who other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe could as wel haue preſerued him, without feeling hunger, as hee did <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Mount, and <hi>Elijah</hi> in his journey.<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 34. &amp; 34. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>g. 19.</note> But this was diſpoſed by God after this manner, to the end, it might bee to the <hi>Prophet</hi> a <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral</hi> and <hi>natural ſigne incurring</hi> into the <hi>ſenſes</hi> for the ſtrengthening of his <hi>faith,</hi> as the <hi>meſſage</hi> of the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſhall be to the true <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> in the middeſt of their <hi>Terrors.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:12429:24"/>And herevpon is it, that no ſooner doth hee pray, but euen before the prayer is paſt his lippes,<note place="margin">Iſa. 38. Act. 10.</note> hee (as <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> and <hi>Cornelius</hi>) receiueth anſwer of <hi>grace,</hi> and <hi>graunt</hi> of his demand, by an <hi>Angelical</hi> meſſage in the hand of a louing and louely <hi>Prophet;</hi> namely, <hi>Hebrewe conuerts confeſſing Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which tidings brought ſhall amaze the <hi>Babilonians,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Reg. 19. Ap. 17.</note> as the tidings of the approach of the <hi>Aethiopians</hi> did <hi>Senna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib</hi> and ſhall turne the hearts of theſe Nations againſt the <hi>Babilonians</hi> (as the <hi>flames</hi> were turned againſt the <hi>fewellers</hi> in the <hi>firſt Period,</hi> and as the <hi>Beaſts,</hi> vnto whom the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were caſt forth to be deuoured in the <hi>ſecond Period,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Euſeb.</hi> Iſa. 66.</note> were turned againſt thoſe that prouoked them) and ſhall deſtroy them; the Saints of God looking on and reioycing.</p>
                  <p>Thus in this <hi>Period</hi> is contained the warres of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> and the viſion of the <hi>New Ieruſalem,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ap. 20. Ap. 21. Ap. 3.</note> and of the <hi>Philadelphian</hi> and <hi>Laodiecian Churches.</hi> That is to ſay, the diſtreſſes of the <hi>Church</hi> by an <hi>Anarchical Apoſtacy,</hi> and the cauſes thereof, with the time of the endurance and meanes of deliuery; the calling and <hi>conuerſion</hi> of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and their vnion vnto the trew Profeſſors of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whereby ſhall be purchaſed <hi>Triumphant</hi> daies. Namely,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Num. 28.</hi> Vpon the ſeuenth day the King went to bewayle Daniel.</note> the <hi>double ſacrifice</hi> due to the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> which is the <hi>ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> of <hi>both Iew and Gentile,</hi> with one heart and mouth prayſing God. And this <hi>Sabbath</hi> neuer did the <hi>Church</hi> yet enjoy, but at length muſt, for a preparation to the end. <hi>Which time haſten ô Lord, thou which art the trew and Aeternal</hi> High Prieſt, <hi>in whom thy</hi> Church <hi>doth cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate a</hi> perpetual Sabbath, <hi>offering themſelues vp a</hi> Holy,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> Liuely, and Gracious Sacrifice, <hi>by their (not Brutiſh but)</hi> Reaſonable <hi>and</hi> Intelligent <hi>ſeruice of God. Euen ſo Lord</hi> IESV, <hi>come quickly.</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:12429:25"/>
               <head>The firſt Corollary.</head>
               <p>IN the meane ſpace; the Light that this <hi>Parabolical Prophecie</hi> doth illuminate vs with, is: That all the members of the <hi>Church</hi> of God <hi>generally,</hi> and euery one <hi>ſeuerally</hi> bee hereby informed to a due conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the <hi>ſtate,</hi> wherein they preſently ſtand; either for their <hi>ſpirit</hi> of their <hi>inmoſt conſcience,</hi> or for the <hi>priuate</hi> of their <hi>worldly ſtate,</hi> or for the <hi>publique</hi> of the <hi>politique ſociety,</hi> wherein they liue. And that they doe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly diſpoſe of themſelues. Firſt, whether ſuffering <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Period. </seg>1</label> in the <hi>fornace</hi> of Gods tryals, that they abide <hi>conſtant,</hi> rather to dye then to fall from their hope. Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Period. </seg>2</label> whether brought into vndeſerued <hi>Obloquy,</hi> that they pacify themſelues out of the <hi>teſtimony</hi> of a <hi>cleere conſcience.</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Period. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, whether in <hi>Authority,</hi> that in the <hi>firſt</hi> place, they aduance the <hi>honor</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> that hath aduanced them vnto <hi>honor</hi> aboue others. Or laſtly, whether in the <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Period. </seg>4</label> midſt of a <hi>Brute-hearted</hi> generation, that they bee not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way diſmayed, but cheere themſelues, in aſſurance, that the power of their <hi>Aduerſaries</hi> is limited, and ſhall not bee able to ſtretch it ſelfe farther, then ſhall bee for the <hi>honour of God, and good of his faithfull ſeruants. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring this withal, that ſo long as wee giue our ſelues ouer to the Purſuite of our</hi> priuate ends, <hi>ſo long ſhall wee bee left to the danger of theſe our</hi> Brutiſh <hi>Enemies. But ſo ſoone as the Day-ſtarre of the Lords</hi> Sabbath <hi>ſhall ariſe in our Hearts, and wee</hi> by the conduct thereof, ſeeke his face, <hi>leaueing our owne ſelfe wranglings:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa 148. Iſa. 60. Ap. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>The whole creature ſhall ioyne with vs vnto a perfect celebration thereof. And of that</hi> Sabbath <hi>day ſhall be no Sun-ſet: for</hi> Chriſt our righteouſneſſe <hi>ſhall euer more and more lighten vs vnto Triumph,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>and treading downe of our Enemies, Death, and all, vnder our feete, in him and by him.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:12429:25"/>
                  <hi>But</hi> — Paulo maiora.</q>
               <p>Here is in this <hi>Quadripartite Parable</hi> deſcribed vnto vs a fourefold <hi>ſtate</hi> of the <hi>man</hi> in <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt is the <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Natural Propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</note> originally deriued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him from his <hi>Parents;</hi> touching which, are the the words of the <hi>Prophet: In iniquity was I formed, and conceiued in ſin.</hi> Out of the remembrance whereof,<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note> ſo long as hee beholdeth himſelfe as in that <hi>ſtate,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The fyary for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace.</note> he find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing in himſelfe but <hi>fights</hi> (of his owne guilty conſcience) <hi>within, and feares (of the whole Creature cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for Iuſtice againſt the Man for his abuſe of them) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out;</hi> Thus euery where bearing about in the body, the <hi>dying</hi> of our Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> by his afflicted <hi>ſpirit.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.</note> Onely the zeale of his inward <hi>LOVE,</hi> the feruor whereof is farre more mightie, then to be inuaded by outward and <hi>Elementiſh</hi> conſiderations, maketh him a <hi>freſhure,</hi> as vnto theſe young men in the midſt of the <hi>flammes</hi> in the <hi>firſt Period.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>ſecond</hi> is,<note place="margin">Adoption and Spiritual Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note> the ſtate of his <hi>Adoption</hi> and <hi>Childhood</hi> in <hi>Chriſt</hi> through <hi>Grace.</hi> By the meanes whereof, euen in his greateſt weakeneſſe, hee ſaluteth (as it were a farre of) the louely Reuelations of God vnto him, in ſuch liberal manner as hee is ouercome, and in feare to bee puffed vp by them. And therefore it is good for him,<note place="margin">The falſe Iudges.</note> yet to indure the <hi>buffetings of Satan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.</note> whereby the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is ſealed vnto him, that the <hi>grace of Chriſt is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for him,</hi> as the <hi>Chaſt wife</hi> doth in the ſecond <hi>Period.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>third</hi> is,<note place="margin">Man-hood and Strength.</note> his <hi>full growth</hi> and ſtrength of manhood in <hi>Christ,</hi> whereby hee is able with all Saints to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, what is the <hi>bredth, length, depth and height:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>and to know the loue of Chriſt, which paſſeth all knowlage.</hi> And therefore from the former <hi>Period,</hi> of being able <hi>to Suffer,</hi> hee is now growne to bee able <hi>to Doe.</hi> Namely, to caſt downe <hi>(Belus) Imaginations,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.</note> and euery high thing that exalteth it ſelfe againſt the knowlage of God, and to bring into <hi>captiuity (the Dragon, and)</hi> euery thought to the obedience of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> So that by times,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12429:26"/>
euen at his firſt comming into the entertainment of <hi>Cyrus (Chriſt riſen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Belus and his Dragon.</note> 
                  <hi>aſcended,</hi> and <hi>reigning in him)</hi> hee taketh away all the vngodly out of the Land, and doth cut of all the wicked doers from the <hi>City of the Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 101.</note> And this Citie, is not onely his outward ranke in the world: but the inward man of him, as hee is the <hi>Temple of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and thoſe wicked ones are the many bayts, ſuggeſtions, exceſſes, and wants, as well within him, as round about him. In all which, hee now can ſay with the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Phil. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>I can doe all things by him that ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth mee,</hi> as wee finde it the part of all <hi>Daniels</hi> to doe, in the third <hi>Period.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Perfection.</note>The fourth is, the <hi>glory</hi> of the <hi>mans conſumation.</hi> By the which [<hi>although hee doe yet walke in the fleſh</hi> (aſſayled on euery ſide with the <hi>ſpurres</hi> thereof, as with ſo many <hi>Lyons</hi>),<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.</note> notwithſtanding <hi>[hee doth not warre after the fleſh]</hi> that hee ſhould ſtand in feare of them,<note place="margin">The Den of Lyons</note> or bee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyed by them, becauſe hee liueth in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And for as much as hee is able in the brightneſſe of a good conſcience, to beare witneſſe to himſelfe with the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle [I haue kept the faith;]</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim 4.</note> therefore doth hee conclude, that <hi>[neither tribulation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>nor diſtreſſe, nor perſecution, nor famine, nor nakedneſſe, nor peril, nor ſword, ſhall ſeperate betwixt Chriſt and him.] For</hi> in all theſe, <hi>wee are more then conquerors,</hi> as wee finde <hi>Daniel</hi> amidſt the <hi>Lyons,</hi> in the fourth <hi>Period.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And euen this very <hi>Myſterie</hi> is it, that a right learned and vertuous<note n="*" place="margin">Mr. Edmund Spencer. The great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment I ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times enioyed by his Sweete ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſuffereth not this to paſſe me, without Reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iue mention of ſo trew a friend. Sine nomine Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus. The young men in the fyar.</note> Gentleman hath ſo liuely decyphered, in his <hi>Legend</hi> of the <hi>Patron of trew holineſſe,</hi> the <hi>Knight of the Red-Croſſe;</hi> whereby, and by the reſt of thoſe his louely <hi>Raptures,</hi> hee hath juſtly purchaſed the <hi>Lawrel</hi> of <hi>honorable memory,</hi> while the Pilgrimage of thoſe his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies are to indure.</p>
               <p>Hee there hath brought forth our <hi>Noble Saint George;</hi> at the firſt onely in the ſtate of a <hi>Swayne,</hi> before his <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Queene</hi> caſt downe on the ground <hi>[Vncouth, vnkeſt] Vnacknowne, vncared off</hi> as a dead trunke, and onely fit for the <hi>fire</hi> (as in our firſt <hi>Period</hi>).</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:12429:26"/>But when hee had arrayed himſelfe in the <hi>Armor</hi> of his Dying Lord, his preſence is then become <hi>Gracious,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Chaſt wife accuſed and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> and his Perſon promiſing great things <hi>[as one for ſad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters fit].</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Belus and his Prieſts ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> Which hee firſt <hi>Paſſiuely</hi> (as in our ſecond <hi>Period</hi>), and after <hi>Actiuely</hi> (as in our third <hi>Period</hi>) doth ſo victoriouſly paſſe through and finiſh; that at the length (as in our fourth <hi>Period,</hi>) hee is become altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Impaſſible,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Daniel amids the Lyons vntouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> whether of <hi>Aſſalts</hi> of the fraylety of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> within, or <hi>Affronts</hi> of <hi>Aduerſaries</hi> without, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fully poſſeſſed of that Kingdome, againſt which there is none to ſtand vp.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond Corollary.</head>
               <p>BY that which hath beene ſaide, is made manifeſt, how exactly theſe <hi>Apocryphal Prophecies</hi> of <hi>Daniel</hi> doe agree. Firſt, with the <hi>Prophecies,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sacra Scriptura dum narrat geſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, trodit Myſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erium.</note> 
                  <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> and <hi>Prophetical Hiſtories</hi> of the <hi>Canonical Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, with the gracious <hi>Speculations</hi> and <hi>Obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of the <hi>Religiouſly learned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, with the <hi>Accompliſhments</hi> of them all from time to time. And ſo (according to the <hi>Law,</hi> that <hi>In the mouth of two or three witneſſes the trewth be stabliſhed</hi>) how worthily they haue to chalenge to themſelues,<note place="margin">Deut. 19.5.</note> their <hi>ancient</hi> place and right. Namely, if not to goe <hi>[promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuè]</hi> with the <hi>Sacred Scriptures,</hi> as they formerly did; yet to hold their <hi>attendance</hi> on them <hi>inſeperable,</hi> aboue all other writings whatſoeuer. And how dangerouſly any ſhall preſume <hi>to diuorce them,</hi> which haue beene found yoaked and drawing together, <hi>ſo many ages of the Church of God, inconſtant and vn-interrupted ſucceſſion.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their coupling together, may be judged to haue beene the <hi>worke of God,</hi> and not of <hi>man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But for farther confirmation of a thing already ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, let vs adde <hi>[ex abundanti]</hi> one Teſtimony more,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12429:27"/>
whether as <hi>neceſſary</hi> as the former, I forbeare to ſay, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely no leſſe <hi>Gracious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The wonderfull <hi>Light</hi> (I meane) exhibited vnto vs from Heauen by the late <hi>Prodigious Comete,</hi> according to the ſeueral <hi>differences</hi> to bee conſidered in it. Namely,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>The Influence of its Compound receiued from the Aethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real bodyes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>The peculiar motion allotted vnto it.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>The large progreſſe ouer the heads of ſo many Nations.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>The ſundry conſtellations it viſited in progreſſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. <hi>The different Extention of his trayne.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6. <hi>The great distance of it from this Habitable of Mortality.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>7. <hi>Laſtly, the place of Exſpiring and Diſparition.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>In all which it hath by <hi>Diuine Characters</hi> and <hi>Lynes</hi> drawne in the <hi>Heauens</hi> (that all <hi>Mortals</hi> might by them be made <hi>Inexcuſable</hi>) preached vnto vs, the <hi>Approach</hi> and <hi>Accompliſhment</hi> of thoſe workes of the <hi>Creators proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> which were ſo <hi>long before</hi> ordained and reuealed, that they ſhould bee performed in their due time. To the worldlings, and to them that put their truſt and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent</hi> in the vncertaintie of <hi>Tranſitory</hi> things, <hi>Diſmal</hi> and <hi>Deſolatory,</hi> according to the word of God by his <hi>Prophet, [They ſhall ſay to the Mountaines couer vs, and to the Hills, fall vpon vs.]</hi> But to the trewly faithfull, and thoſe that haue in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> crucified themſelues to the world, <hi>full of ioy</hi> and comfort, according to the word of their Lord, <hi>[when theſe things begin to come to paſſe;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>then looke vp, and lift vp your heads; for your Redemption draweth nigh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For proofe whereof, let vs make a <hi>Superficial Eſſay</hi> of ſome few.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ara, Lar. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>The <hi>Original</hi> of it, eſteemed neere to the <hi>Conſtellation</hi> of <hi>[The Altar,]</hi> and as it were bred out of the <hi>ſmoake</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; As it ſeemeth to declare that the worldlings vnder <hi>pretenſe</hi> of <hi>Relligion</hi> did put themſelues into <hi>Secret Combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations</hi> and in manner of <hi>Relligious vowes</hi> for the Proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their pernicious <hi>calumnies,</hi> and vniuſt Perſecutions againſt their <hi>Enemies</hi> the <hi>Faithfull</hi> now more then euer:<note place="margin">Sap. 2.12.</note>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:12429:27"/>
So in like manner it putteth the <hi>Godly</hi> in mind of the <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Altar</hi> from <hi>vnder</hi> which the Soules of the Bleſſed <hi>Martyrs</hi> cal for <hi>vengeance;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ap. 6.</note> and the <hi>Gratious anſwere</hi> they receiue for <hi>Confirmation</hi> of vs that are left behind.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Influence</hi> it receiued from the <hi>Planetary Lights</hi> in the Generation of it as in the Euil,<note place="margin">Oppoſ. with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Coniunction with, ♂ and ☿.</note> it ſheweth their <hi>ouer-growne Frowardneſſe, Infidelity,</hi> and <hi>Raſhneſſe:</hi> So in the <hi>Pious</hi> it portendeth their <hi>Conſtancy, Princely Patience, Martiall valor</hi> and <hi>boldneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Ingenious Compaſſes</hi> for their diſcreete and Conuenient <hi>Ends.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Luſtre</hi> it gathered at the firſt by <hi>Reflection</hi> on <hi>Cauda Pauonis</hi> as in a <hi>Mirraur</hi> ſheweth that notwithſtanding the <hi>Pretext of Holineſſe</hi> the <hi>Hypocrites</hi> make:<note place="margin">Cauda Pauonis.</note> yet it is wholy to aduance the <hi>Painted plumes</hi> of ſome whether <hi>Peacocke</hi> or <hi>Auſtriche,</hi> that diſplay their gay fethers more for vaine ſhew then for any gratious vſe they put them to.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Conſtellations</hi> is paſſeth through;<note place="margin">Lupus and ♏.</note> Firſt <hi>Wolfe</hi> and <hi>Scorpion,</hi> in the <hi>Euil</hi> is ſigne of their <hi>Rabide</hi> and veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſe <hi>Implacability</hi> againſt the <hi>Saints;</hi> But in the <hi>Good</hi> their <hi>Inward Ardor</hi> in <hi>Piety</hi> towards their <hi>Godly Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> as <hi>Iacob</hi> fortelleth of his <hi>Louely Son</hi> the <hi>Wolfe Beniamin;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen 44.</note> and their <hi>outward help</hi> from <hi>God</hi> againſt their Enemies, as was vnto the <hi>Iſraelites amids fiery Serpents, Scorpions,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 8.15.</note> and drought in the wilderneſſe.</p>
               <p>The not appearing of the Comet during his being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnder the <hi>Conſtellation</hi> of <hi>Libra</hi> (becauſe he was then vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>beames</hi> of the Sun) doth touching the <hi>Euil,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In ♎ ſub radijs ☉ is.</note> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the <hi>Summons</hi> of them to declare, and a <hi>Compulſion</hi> of them to ſpeake <hi>openly</hi> their <hi>Deſignes,</hi> by <hi>Legall Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Ambaſſyes, Treatyes,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">The trayne of it towards ♍.</note> which (by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of his <hi>Trayne</hi> to the <hi>Characteriſme</hi> of <hi>Virgo</hi>) are then manifeſted to be intended againſt the <hi>Church [eo nomine] as it is the flocke of Chriſt:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>☉ is motus a ♏ in ♐.</p>
                     <p>Motus Cometae a ♏ in ♎ &amp; inde ♍ verſus.</p>
                  </note> On the other ſide to the <hi>Good</hi> it ſheweth that howſoeuer by the Sunnes going <hi>forward</hi> (according to the Order of the Signes) in the <hi>Zodiaque,</hi> and the <hi>Comets Retrogradation (againſt</hi> the Order of the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12429:28"/>
Signes (God doth ſeeme to leaue the wicked to their Counſels, with free liberty to purſue them; yet doth he neuertheleſſe <hi>impoſe</hi> a <hi>Seuere reſtreint</hi> of their Malice by Order of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> that it ſhall not bring any damage to his <hi>Spouſe</hi> the <hi>Mayden-Mother Queene his Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Serpens.</note>Herevpon the Comete by his Northward way is carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the <hi>Serpent</hi> by which he is <hi>ſtung</hi> and pricked forward (for then the Comete is ſeene in the <hi>Mornings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and his <hi>Motion</hi> is become <hi>moſt ſwift</hi>) ſhewing that the Euil find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Projects fruſtrate in manner as is aboue ſhewed, ſhould change their <hi>priuy Conſpiracies</hi> into <hi>open Hoſtilities,</hi> which they ſhould purſue in moſt violent manner, &amp; by the greateſt ſtrength they were able to make or procure: But to the <hi>Godly</hi> it ſheweth that by meanes of the <hi>Noble Serpent [Dan</hi> the <hi>Iudge]</hi> the more Expedition and Strength their Enemies ſhould vſe,<note place="margin">Gen. 44.</note> the ſooner ſhould they be diſſolued and vaniſh by the <hi>Chariot</hi> and <hi>Horſe-men of Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Reg. 13.</note> as the Comet in his comming to Bootes and the Reſt of thoſe <hi>Polar Characters</hi> is ſeene to languiſh:<note place="margin">Arctophilax &amp;c.</note> And ſo by a ſlower <hi>Motion</hi> and through a Part of the Heauens <hi>not honoured with Conſtellations</hi> (as through a <hi>Deſert</hi> of <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuritie</hi>)<note place="margin">Vrſa maior &amp;c.</note> to hide the head.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Cauda Draconis.</note>Laſtly, the Comet drawing to the taile of the <hi>Dragon</hi> is by the Light of the <hi>New Moone</hi> (then gathering ſtrength) wholy darkned,<note place="margin">Nouilunium.</note> his body diſperſed, and his <hi>fire quenched.</hi> Shewing that howeuer the Euil doe yet a <hi>third time</hi> ſeeke to gather more new poyſon from the <hi>Old Dragon</hi> (and the Purple <hi>Harlot</hi> his Rider the <hi>founder</hi> of all their Practiſes) yet it ſhall not be <hi>her Naſty skirts</hi> that ſhall ſerue to releiue or ſhelter them, but by the <hi>Brightneſſe of the Church,</hi> comming forth as a <hi>Bride</hi> out of her <hi>Chamber,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Gratious as the Morning, faire as the Moone, pure as the Sun, and terrible as the Banners of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanaijm</hi> (Men and Angels,<note place="margin">Gen. 32.</note> or Angelical Men) they ſhal be vtterly fruſtrate and end in a <hi>Smoke</hi> and <hi>Stench</hi> as the <hi>Comete</hi> then did.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:12429:28"/>Theſe few (as I ſaid) haue I for an <hi>Eſſay</hi> thought good to touch vpon: which how trew they haue beene vnto vs thus farre, and how fully they doe ſquare with the <hi>Captiuity</hi> of our Prophet in his <hi>laſt Period</hi> I neede not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large. As alſo that (no leſſe in euery ones <hi>Particular</hi> then as before in the <hi>Generall</hi>) it is in the <hi>faculty</hi> of Men to make vſe hereof (if they liſt) to their <hi>Priuate</hi> counſels.</p>
               <p>Neither let any vnderpriſe theſe as no more then <hi>volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Applications:</hi> For if they thinke that eyther the Names <hi>firſt</hi> allotted to theſe <hi>Conſtellations</hi> were <hi>[Sine Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine]</hi> things wherein God had not a <hi>Speciall</hi> hand; Or that they were not ſo <hi>Diſtributed</hi> into <hi>Characters</hi> by <hi>Diuine Inſpiration;</hi> Or laſtly, that theſe <hi>Caeleſtial Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritions</hi> haue not <hi>Reference</hi> nor Enterview with <hi>this Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> Orbe: Let all ſuch vnderſtand, that how much ſo euer knowlage whether of <hi>Humane</hi> or <hi>Diuine</hi> Letters they haue ſcraped vp together: They haue not yet ſo much as by ſight <hi>aloofe</hi> ſaluted the threſhold of <hi>Trew wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes Sanctuary.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 9.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>NOw therefore for Concluſion, let euery one as he ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth his trew &amp; Aeternal good, ſettle himſelfe thrif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily &amp; carefully to ſearch into his owne heart, &amp; that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wearineſſe or Intermiſſion, vntil he finde in which of theſe 4. wayes of our <hi>Prophets Parables</hi> he ſtandeth, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly ſhape his Courſe. With this reſt to be laid vp, that if in order as to the <hi>Church,</hi> he finde not the world vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him as in one of theſe <hi>States;</hi> or that in order as to himſelfe, he beare not himſelfe as by theſe <hi>precedents</hi> he is informed; The ſame man hath no comfort out of this <hi>Prophecy,</hi> nor out of any other that doth <hi>Analogize</hi> with it.</p>
               <p>And ſuch are the ſcorners of theſe times, whom the <hi>God</hi> of this world hath ſo blinded, that they begin to ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12429:29"/>
as ſome did of old <hi>[where is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>]</hi> Things are to day as they were yeſter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhalbe to morrow as they are to day.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> If we ſhal be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued we ſhal be ſaued, let vs liue as we liſt, and ſo moch at <hi>Reproofe</hi> and hate the <hi>Reproouer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh</hi> that there were not ſo many of them in theſe dayes, which turne the ſweeteſt juices of <hi>Wit, Learninge, Tongues, Fauor, Strength, Honor, Wealth, Place,</hi> yea <hi>Relligion</hi> and all into the floaty <hi>Gall</hi> of vpbraiding and contemning others. As I ſurmiſe there wil not be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſome that wil doe of this my Labour: vnto whom (if any be) I reply none otherwiſe then thus; That there are yet other things enfolded in this <hi>Prophecy</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining to the <hi>Influence</hi> of a <hi>Different Climat,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mundus alter &amp; idem.</note> which by the Rule of <hi>Prophetical wiſedome;</hi> and <hi>Sacred Sobriety</hi> in <hi>Spiritual</hi> matters are not to be entruſted to Paper and Enke;<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 13.</note> and therefore haue I in them followed (I hope vpon good warrant) the Apoſtles Rule of <hi>Reſeruation.</hi> Now my requeſt to theſe men is, that they firſt pleaſe to make <hi>Eſſayes</hi> of their owne <hi>Illuminations</hi> vnto the Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of thoſe things. Which if they atteine vnto, it ſhal be to me a double comfort that I ſhal enioy their brotherly concurrence, whereby more hopefully then by my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle ſtrength may be endeauoured the ſhortning of thoſe Dayes which our <hi>Sauiour</hi> hath declared out of his incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible loue and care ouer his <hi>Elect</hi> to be expedient that they be ſhortened vnto which worke euery good Chriſtian is bound to conſpire.</p>
               <p>And herein I doe in the bowells of <hi>Christ Ieſus</hi> deſire theſe my deere brethren, that laying aſide al bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſuperfluity of Malice they wil joyne with me; That ſo in them and in me and in al that loue the comming of our Lord may be heard the <hi>Melodious Harmony</hi> of the <hi>Angels</hi> Singing, <hi>GLORY TO GOD IN THE HIGHEST.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
